where they called themselves Vincentian priests and everything.
So they followed the Vincentian tradition.
And I think the people that founded the university
were part of that Vincentian tradition.
So these are priests from France, actually.
Huh.
You never know.
Yeah.
I know that that's supposed to be a cross or something.
That's a really good cross.
Oh, I see.
It's like the tree.
It's like the tree of giving.
I thought there was a tree.
I think it's a tree.
I should know the symbols.
I don't know.
I think it is some sort of either flower or tree or something,
but I don't remember what it stood for.
That's a very good question.
It was a very good question, actually.
I'll inform myself and then bring you the answer next time.
Or we can probably ask your GPT.
Yeah, and it's the purpose of the conversation.
Exactly.
Well, right.
There's some questions that don't need to be answered.
And they say that the students don't make the professor, you know, don't give them homework
assignments then the class is wasted, so definitely you gotta give me homework assignments.
All right, let me go ahead and open D2L.
It started shortly.
This is week three?
I think this is week four, because it starts on a Wednesday.
Yeah, so quiz three, week four, because the first week doesn't get a quiz.
At least that's how I remember.
So technically this has 11 weeks in the class?
If you include the exams week, yes, it will be 11 weeks.
So 10 weeks of lectures and homework assignments and stuff, and then one week for exams.
All right. Well, let's go ahead and start the lecture. So welcome back to Distributed Systems 1.
Let's start with announcements first. So you had programming assignment 1 was due last night at midnight.
Programming assignment 2 was due next week on Tuesday at midnight.
And then quiz number 3 was also posted this morning. So you have until Monday to complete it.
Quiz number 3 will cover architectural style section from chapter 2.
So basically what we talked about last week after we talked about programming assignment 2.
So only the logical parts.
I know, I think we still have to discuss about the publisher-subscriber model.
So we'll talk about it today.
Today would be more of a theoretical set of lectures, you know.
So anyways, bear with me.
If you need another coffee, just grab it.
I'll try to make it as interactive as I can.
And then what we'll do is next week after the deadline of programming assignment 2,
release programming assignment 3 and we'll spend some time talking about it so there's gonna be a
little bit more practical elements too but before we start that you know any questions regarding
programming assignment 2 the quiz the class anything you want i'd be happy to take them
yes um no you don't have to hey you know why is i talk too much i feel like sometimes like it's
okay that's fine that's good but i have a tendency during the quizzes so like
I overthink something and I choose the wrong one and I get like three out of four.
And that would, after you do it over a longer period of time,
that's going to really seriously affect things.
So the bonus is designed to add points to the, that's what you'd say.
To the quizzes, yeah.
So basically the extra credit quiz is one additional quiz.
It's worth the same amount of points as the rest of the quizzes.
And when I calculate the points,
I accumulate all of the points from all the quizzes,
and then I cap it at 20 points maximum.
Okay, so it's just basically a way to make up for...
Yes.
Yeah, I think as the quarter will go,
I think the questions will get easier.
So anyways, there will be more maybe intense at the beginning,
but then I think things will get easier.
The assignments will get more difficult,
so it balances itself out.
Okay, but I think after you do a few quizzes,
you're going to get a hang of it.
And I don't know if this is something that is obvious, but you can go to D2L.
So on every Wednesday at midnight in one minute, what I do is I also open up a display view on D2L.
So you can go to your attempt and you can see the questions with the answers and what was correct and what was wrong.
So you can use that to review materials before the exam as well because the exam will have questions from the quizzes.
so make sure that you check that as well so at least you can get a hang of the questions okay
all right very good any other questions i wanted to ask programming assignment is very similar to
this databases and sql the language not well it looks like that it kind of looks like that so
actually it looks more like so when you take a database class i think there are three ways you
can take the database class. So you can take an intro to databases where you learn about, you
know, SQL, relational algebra, you know, that kind of stuff. Then you can take a more advanced
database where you learn about query optimization and, you know, more advanced ways of organizing
database management systems. Or the third option is you can take a class where you learn how to
build a database. So this would be more similar to learning how you build a database, but
you're actually building a search engine, not a database.
So the search engines are a little bit different.
So they have some things in common.
They use the notion of indexes,
while a database uses indexes to order the data
so that you can accelerate, you know, the processing of the queries.
But again, a database, right, structures, right,
organizes data in a structured format, right.
So SQL stands for standard query language, right,
It follows relational algebra, and there are a few implementations of the SQL language out there, right?
But the basic concept is that you're organizing the data under a form of tables, right?
And you have a relationship between tables or between columns of those tables, right?
Primary key, foreign key, right?
That kind of stuff.
And then what the databases do is they allow you to run custom queries.
So you can, you know, query the database.
You can select things from the database.
You can select subsets of the data from the database.
You can do calculations when you select the subsections of the database.
So it gives you a very rich language.
Now, a search engine, the purpose of the search engine is to actually organize unstructured data.
So databases are structured data.
You might have heard of NoSQL databases like MongoDB.
Those are classified as semi-structured data, where you specify your structure dynamically as you're adding the objects in the database.
And then you have unstructured data like books and reports and emails and whatever.
This is, again, it doesn't follow always a specific structure, and it uses natural language.
So the purpose of the search engine is to reorganize the data in a way where you can now search that unstructured data.
Now, information retrieval is the main field that studies how do you build search engines
and how do you create information retrieval models.
However, there's also areas that now fall in the area of data science, but they used to be called data mining before, where you basically try to extract structure from unstructured data, or try to detect structure from unstructured data.
So data mining includes knowledge extraction, where you detect entities and relations between them, building knowledge graphs, but also doing key means clustering and that kind of stuff.
Nowadays, when it comes to information retrieval, people use more modern techniques.
So instead of using classical information retrieval models, we use neural information retrieval models.
So in the world of natural language processing, they discover these artificial intelligence models
that can build an embedding space where you're representing words and sentences and documents
in some sort of n-dimensional space that is in a reduced space,
so it has maybe 384 dimensions,
that's the usual dimension space that they create.
And then what they do is they create this, again,
artificial neural network where that captures meaning from words.
But the meaning, it's not the same meaning that we ascribe to words.
The meaning means that the words that are closer to each other in sentences,
it means that they are similar in terms of meaning.
And by training, you know, a large model, you know,
on, you know, data from the internet, let's say, for example,
you can then build these embedding systems
that can encode the words in dimensional spaces
and then you can find similarity between words,
between paragraphs, between documents
by just looking at the vectors in that end dimensional space.
so I think right now there is a people don't fully understand you know in which situations
it's better to use classical information retrieval versus neural information retrieval
this is an active area of research and actually I do have a student that graduated that took my
class many years ago and he decided to work on a master's thesis with me and we actually looked at
you know what is the performance of these neural information retrieval systems when compared to
classic of the information retrieval.
So anyways, I hope
that I've given you, again, it's a long
answer. I like to talk a lot. It's a professional defect.
Okay, but hopefully this will give you
a little bit of a bigger picture answer
to your question. Okay?
All right. Very good. Any other questions?
All right. If not,
then I'm going to
skip the discussion about programming
assignment 2. Again, keep in mind,
again, the deadline is on
Tuesday,
so we do have office hours on Monday there are three slots available left so
if you need the office hours I can make sure you allocate them at a time but
I was in some office hours tomorrow ok but anyways I would recommend that you
start working on programming assignment 2 as soon as you can I know you just
maybe finish programming assignment 1 but start early the assignment itself it's
not very difficult like the components that they have to implement not
difficult it's just a lot of code that they have to write and that has to work
well that gets glued together let's see between the different layers so that's
That's why I would recommend starting earlier and then even if you finish the assignment,
keep in mind, you have to do a performance evaluation as well.
That will also take some time, depending on how fast your program is.
I think I've heard students were indexing on Dataset 3 depending on the implementation,
maybe it took 30 minutes to run.
You have to run and let it do indexing and takes a long time.
It just depends on the implementation, how efficient it is.
So I would, again, highly recommend that you start working on this assignment better.
And then if you do need an extension, just let me know,
because I know you overlap with programming assignment one.
I'll need a quorum, so 30%, I think, of the students in class.
If I receive emails that they have, like, an extension, I'll give an extension.
Okay?
All right.
Very good.
Otherwise, let's go ahead and continue talking about architectures and distributed systems.
So last week, we started talking about logical architectures, and we talked first about layered architectures.
We described various ways you can organize layered architectures.
As an example, we used application layering, which is a very popular architecture for organizing applications at a logical level.
After that, we talked about object-based styles or service-oriented architectures.
pictures. So here instead of organize the application as layers, we organize them as
independent components or objects, and each object has its own interface, each object has its own
state and methods that it runs, and then the objects, they can use each other's services by
making calls to their interfaces. This follows the object-oriented, let's say, programming
paradigm or lessons learned from the object-oriented programming paradigm.
And then as an example of a service-oriented architecture, we have, of course, the REST
architecture.
So REST uses the notion that the distributive system will manage some resources.
So the components inside the distributive system are just responsible with managing
resources, which means that in order to operate on these resources, we create a universal
interface. So the interface
basically provides
mechanisms to create new resources,
to read resources, modify resources,
and delete resources, using
the familiar put, get, delete, and post
operations that you see in web applications.
And then if
you can build some sort of
naming schema
in your system, then you can identify
a resource uniquely, and then you can
do operations. The advantage
of this approach over the
object-oriented interface is that when you submit an operation, you do one of
those four operations of a unique identifier and then inside the message of
this request you include the details of whatever operation you do on the
object. So if you need to add extra information to the object or if you need
attributes, for example, for objects, you know, permissions, share settings, you know,
you can do that by adding extra information in the message.
This means that the applications, they just have to process a piece of text and extract
all of the valuable information from it, which allows you to use a universal interface, makes
it very easy to add new services.
With the object-oriented interface, right, whenever you change the application programming
interface, you need to change the applications as well.
otherwise they won't be able to compile or run.
All right.
But, and I think we stop here at the coordination part.
So, so far, when we talked about these logical architectures,
we didn't make any assumption about, you know,
the components that are either layers or objects.
When do they communicate with each other?
Do they have to, you know, when they communicate,
does a component need to know exactly
with which other component does it need to communicate with?
So this falls in the area of coordination between components inside the distributed system.
So all of these questions, how do the components have to be up and running at the same time?
Does a component need to know where to find another component?
These are all valid questions, and there are questions that are in the area of coordination.
So it's important to understand the problem of coordination because then it will allow
to actually define some more interesting, let's say, logical ways for organizing distributed applications.
So when it comes to coordination, there are two, let's say, factors that matter
when it comes to how two components can communicate with each other.
So there is a temporal factor.
So the temporal factor refers to, okay, are the components,
they have to be up and running at the same time in order for them to be able to communicate?
or can one of the components be offline
and the communication can still happen?
I'll give some examples of what that means.
And then lastly, the referential factor refers to
does a component need to know exactly
which other component does it need to communicate with
or can he send a message to
and any component can pick it up?
We'll see some examples of where this is useful.
So in the book, the authors, they call these
temporal and referential couplings.
And you can have two variants of, you know,
temporal couplings.
So you can have systems that have components
that are temporally coupled versus temporally decoupled,
and then components that are referentially coupled
and referentially decoupled.
This creates now four categories of coordination
in distributive systems.
So let's start with the first one.
So the direct coordination model refers to
systems where the components are temporally coupled and referentially coupled.
So it means that the components inside the distributive system, and when they communicate
with each other, so temporally coupled means that they have to be up and running at the
same time, and referentially coupled, you need that component initiates a request.
It needs to know exactly what is the destination component.
So as an example of the direct coordination model, we can use the cell phone system, right?
So for example, if you want to be able to call someone, right, you need to know who you're calling.
You cannot just call somebody in the ETA, right?
You need to have a destination phone number that you're calling.
So that's what it means by referentially coupled.
You have to have a destination.
And then temporary coupled means that both phones have to be up and running and connected to the network for the call to go through.
If one of the phones is not connected to the network or is shut off, the call will not go through.
You will get immediately an indication that, hey, you cannot call this number.
All right.
The mailbox coordination model refers to systems where the components are temporally decoupled but referentially coupled.
So, temporally decoupled means that the components do not have to be up and running at the same time.
the message will still be sent between them
but you have to, again, referentially coupled means that a component needs to know
with which other component does it need to talk to
so as an example, I'm going to use electronic mail, email
as a way to describe
an example for this model
so in the email model, the components represent the people that send
emails between each other
the system is temporally decoupled because I can send an email
to one of my friends, even though they're not connected to their computer right now.
The computer is offline.
The email gets sent somewhere in the server where it gets stored.
So we need some notion of persistency we'll see very shortly.
But whenever I send an email, I cannot send the email to the ether.
I need to send an email to a destination.
The destination could be another email address, could be, for example, an email group.
and the email group will then send an email to each of the members of the group
but in the end we still need a destination.
So this is an example of the mailbox coordination model.
Now when we go to systems that are referentially decoupled
we have two examples here.
We have event-based systems and the shared data space model.
So here, what they both have in common is that they have some sort of event bus
where the components can actually submit the request directly to the event bus.
And then there are other components that can capture those requests from the event bus.
The beauty of it is that when the components communicate with the event bus,
they don't have to have a destination set up.
So that's why the components in these two kinds of coordination models,
they are referentially decoupled.
So a component doesn't necessarily have to know with whom does it need to communicate or with whom does it need to send a request.
Now, the difference between them for temporally coupled means that all of the components have to be up and running at the same time when the communication happens.
Otherwise, the messages get lost on the event bus.
And then in the shared data space coordination model, we have some sort of persistency component that is part of the event bus that can store those messages
until they're ready to be picked up by other systems.
So the components, they can go offline and online whenever they want.
Now, by convention, when we talk about event-based systems,
the components, they can perform two kinds of operations on the event bus.
They can publish information on the event bus,
or they can subscribe to receive information from the event bus.
And then when they subscribe, there are two ways that they can receive information.
the components can wait until the information is available on the event bus.
Or they can tell the event bus, hey, you know, I'm interested in data.
Just notify me when the data is available.
I don't know if we gave as an example last time,
but the way you can understand this event bus is the same way operating systems
allows processes to read data from a disk, right?
So if I were to ask you, you know, how does a process read data from the disk from a file?
What does the process do in order to be able to read data from a disk?
What does a process do and then what does the operating system do?
Or what are the two ways that a process can read data from the disk?
To give you a hint, that the disk is a slower device than the processor itself, right?
So, there are two things that we can do.
I mean, isn't the disk indexed already?
So, the operating system goes to read it.
It's the index of what's on there, so it doesn't read all of the information.
Correct.
But what I'm more interested in is if the disk is slower than the processor, what does
the process do while it's waiting for the data to come from the disk?
Wait.
Wait, yes.
I was just going to say sleep and wait for it.
Sleep and wait, right.
So there are two techniques.
They're called polling and using interrupts.
These are the two techniques.
So polling means that the process will keep on asking the operating system, hey, is the
data ready yet?
So keep in mind that the operating system mediates access to hardware.
So whenever we want to read some data from the disk and bring it to memory,
the process itself cannot do that operation.
It needs to ask the operating system to do the operation on its behalf.
So it sends a message to the operating system,
and then the operating system will go ahead and perform that operation for that process.
So we can do polling where the process keeps on waiting, actively waits.
So it keeps on running on the CPU and keeps on asking the operating system, hey, is the data ready yet?
Is the data ready yet in this memory?
You can ask it, you know, every instruction or you can put a delay, for example.
You can wait, you know, a few hundred milliseconds until you check to see if the data is available.
Again, it depends on the application.
Now, this is not a very efficient technique, right?
Because the processor is wasting time or the process is wasting time on the processor, doing nothing, just waiting for data.
So it might be efficient to actually allow other processes to run at the same time.
What about the background processes that are waiting for the processor?
Can they run at this time when the data is being read?
Yeah, so they can run only if that process goes to sleep voluntarily.
So if the process decides to stay on the processor, it will stay for the allotted quota of time.
By operating systems, they allow each process to run for a very short amount of time.
And we'll talk more about it in Chapter 3, right?
But the other option would be for the process to tell the operating system,
hey, I want this piece of data, and then voluntarily go to sleep
so that other processes can be scheduled on the process.
So then what the operating system does is when the data is available,
it sends a signal to the process to let it know, an interrupter,
let it know, hey, your data is ready, and it wakes up the process, right?
So the signal is sent to some sort of event bus.
So the process becomes a subscriber,
and the operating system becomes the publisher.
The operating system publishes when the data is available
and sends a notification,
and then the component can use a subscribe function
to actually grab the data from the map.
It doesn't really work that way,
but we can imagine it, you know,
at least at an abstract level that it works this way.
All right, so this now allows us to introduce
these notions here,
these two coordination models,
allows us to introduce,
and I'm going to come back to the Linda.
Topal Spaces allows us to introduce the last logical, let's say, architecture
that we will cover in this class, which is the publisher-subscriber architecture.
So in a publisher-subscriber architecture, this is again a logical way of organizing
the distributed application, where our components can be either publishers or subscribers.
The subscribers, they can subscribe to the services provided by the publishers,
and the publishers will publish information.
Now, what's very interesting when compared to the other two architectures
is that we need something else to be able to implement the system.
We need that event bus, plus maybe the persistency if it's required.
So for this, we need to make use of the middleware layer of distributed systems.
If you remember from the first lecture when we talked about
the distribution transparency goal of distributed systems,
We said that we want to build a system, that the distributed system is a system that appears to its users as one single coherent system, and it does this to this implementation of this middleware, which is a layer that allows distributed systems to run across multiple computers with different architectures, different operating systems, and it provides one uniform interface.
The middleware can also be used to implement this coordination,
so to implement either the event bus or the shared data space coordination model.
So now the middleware is responsible with receiving subscription
or publish approbations from the components.
Now, why do we need a publisher subscriber?
Or what is the advantage of this architecture?
The advantage is that the components can join the distributed system
or leave at will without requiring us to reboot the entire distributed system.
If we build it in a layer fashion, if we want to replace one layer with another one,
we will need to, you know, reset the entire distributed system
and replace, you know, all of the function calls to the new layers, right?
This would be very difficult.
And the object-based as well, depending on which objects get modified,
the interface might change, right?
So this means that we have to, you know, reset parts of the distributed system.
With the publisher-subscriber model, the components, right, the publisher and the subscribers, they can be implemented in different ways.
As long as they use the publish and subscribe operations with the middleware, you know, with the event bus, then we're all good.
They can, you know, leave and join, you know, at will.
Now, there are a few properties, of course, when it comes to the publisher-subscriber systems.
So one of the main challenges of this middleware is that it has to solve the problem of how do we match events to the components that subscribe to those events.
We can say that events can be described by an attribute and value.
And then there are two ways we can, let's say, create the subscription model.
So we can do topic-based subscription or content-based subscription.
So topic-based subscription means that a component that is a subscriber will subscribe to all of the events inside the middleware
that are published by publishers in which the attribute has a specific value.
We'll give some examples of what this means.
Content-based means that the attribute has a value that sits inside some sort of range.
each. So, just to give this a short example, let's say that one day you decide that you
want to learn more about, you know, buying and selling microstocks in tech companies,
right? The way you would do this is you would go, you know, create an account, a background
somewhere, and then download some sort of application that is connected to some sort
of server that gives you the latest value of microstocks for, you know, various kinds
of tech companies. With these applications, what you can do is you can also set up push
notifications that whenever there's a change in the stock of a specific company that you're
interested in, you get a notification. So, to know if you want to sell or buy micro stocks from it.
Okay, this is an example of a topic-based subscription system, right? So, the server
that gives you the notifications acts as the middleware. They have, of course, a set of
publishers, which are the companies that keep track of their stocks or third-party companies
that keep track of the value of the stocks that push the notifications in their server.
and then the server would notify all of the applications
that subscribe for those particular companies.
So if I set up my application and say,
hey, I'd like, again, to receive notifications
from when Stock Exchange in Intel, NVIDIA, Microsoft, Apple,
you will receive notifications for them.
So that's an example of topic-based subscription.
For content-based subscription,
it means that I'm creating a more complex query there.
So maybe I want to say that I'm interested actually
in receiving notifications
for like the top 10 companies
in which stocks change.
Top 10 by the value of the stock.
So this is more of a range query now
because now you're interested
in multiple topics, right?
They can change.
They're not staying statically.
So that's an example
of a content-based subscription,
which typically will be harder to implement.
But topic-based and content-based,
they're typically more difficult
to implement,
especially in a distributed middleware, right?
Because you have to keep track of all of the subscribers,
the kind of information that you need,
and then whenever you have a piece of data that gets received by the middleware,
the middleware has to decide to which subscriber to send the data to, right?
You can use, for example, for topic-based subscriptions,
you could probably use some sort of hash table.
If you keep a hash table where the keys is, let's say, you know, an attribute,
and then the values represent all of the subscribers that subscribe for that particular attribute,
then you could probably solve this problem.
Well, for a content-based subscription, it's more hard.
A hash table won't be able to help.
So just keep in mind that when it comes to the publisher-subscriber systems,
it allows you to, again, build an architecture where the components can join and leave at will.
However, the main challenge, especially when designing publisher-subscriber middleware,
is how do you design an efficient system
that can match the events that come in
with the proper subscribers.
So this can sometimes introduce scalability problems, actually.
So you might make your application not run very fast
if you choose to use this approach.
Now, I also have here an example,
and for some reason the slides are out of order,
but it doesn't really matter.
So an example of a publisher subscriber system
can be built using the lean.touple space library.
So this is a Python library that you can download that implements, that gives you a library that allows you to implement, let's say, publisher subscriber systems.
An example that I have here is an example of a blog.
So a blog is an example of a publisher subscriber system.
In a blog, you have one or two people or more, one or more people that act as publishers.
They publish information on the blog.
And then other people subscribe to that information.
may read the blog, right?
So, the end of couple spaces allows you to implement this blog in various ways.
It has three main operations that allows you to interact with the middleware.
So, the end of couple space itself implements the middleware, but it does it on a single
node system.
If you want to go across nodes, I think it does have support nowadays, but you need
to use something else in the example here.
So the three main operations that are supported for the middleware is instead of doing publishing information and subscribing for information, the three main operations are IN, READ, and OUT.
So IN will remove a tuple matching a specific template from the middleware.
The READ operation will obtain a copy of a tuple matching a template from the middleware.
And then OUT will be able to write a tuple T to the tuple space.
So calling out twice in a row leads to storing two copies of a couple, so the in that couple
space is a multi-set, so it allows multiple copies of the exact same data, and then both
the in and read operations are blocking operations, so the call will block until a matching tuple
is found or has become a data.
So this gives you a very simple example of a blog application.
Sorry.
A very simple example of a blog application that's with Bob, Alice, and Chuck.
You know, they all want to create a blog where they can post information and they can read
information.
So you can follow if you want to, you know, set this up on your own computer and test
it, you know, it's a very easy way to build a very simple blog on your system.
You basically import the Linda library.
You connect to the library.
You create a tuple space.
You have to give it a name when you create it.
You connect them to the tuple space.
And then you can do these out or read or in operation.
So out, you're writing tuples to the tuple space.
And when you do it, you can choose a template for the information that you're including there.
So here, for example, the chosen template is that you want to include the user who posts something
in the blog, the topic and then the actual message that is posted in the blog.
Whenever you do read operation you specify the user that you want to read a topic from
and then the topic that you're interested in, and this will return to you some sort of
piece of text if it's available inside the shared topic space.
Ok but anyways, this is a very simple example, but the way you can think about this publisher
subscriber systems is similar to a blog.
Okay.
All right, well, these are the three kinds of architectures that you will find out there,
especially at the logical level.
What I want to do next is talk about the physical architectures of distributed systems, but
before that, since we mentioned a little bit of middleware, it's also worth mentioning
some of the challenges that can appear when designing middleware and then what other,
say, functionality that middleware has, especially when it comes to, again, defining, let's say,
architectures in terms of components.
So we already mentioned the middleware, right?
It's this layer that provides a uniform interface for all of the applications that are running
on top of this over-distributing system.
The layer itself can run across multiple computers that can have different operating systems and
library versions and CPU architectures in the middle,
where we'll provide a common language between all of them.
It will allow applications to either communicate with other applications
using that common interface,
or will allow a larger application to run across multiple computers as well.
So the distributed system typically contains commonly used components
and functions that need not be implemented by applications separately.
So inside the database, we include a set of common functions and components that all of the applications work on.
Now, one of the main, or one of the challenges that appears when designing middleware,
and when implementing distributed systems, is the problem of having to integrate an interface with legacy applications.
So, as we mentioned before, a distributed system is a system that will grow in size in order to satisfy some sort of requirement, a number of users or a number of requests, right?
And then we have decentralized systems that increase in size in order to integrate other systems together, right?
So especially in the decentralized, let's say, systems world, there's going to be the
chance that you would encounter that you would need to integrate your system with another
existing system, but that uses different kinds of libraries, maybe older version of
those libraries, uses older version of programming languages, and you have to now interface with
those languages.
So in order to be able to interface with them, since you've designed already a distributed
and you have a set of functions and a set of components that speak a certain language,
means that if you want to interact with the other components,
you have to figure out a way to bridge that gap.
So the solution inside distributed systems is to implement wrappers or adapters for legacy components.
So for components that do not offer an appropriate interface,
what we do is we create a wrapper or adapter interface on top of that component.
Now, when creating, let's say, wrappers, there are, of course, a few challenges that can appear depending on what strategy you use to implement the wrappers.
So let's say that we have a distributive system with three components and an application that needs to interact with the distributive system.
If the application wants to interact with the distributive system, the application needs to be able to interact with each of the three components.
The components also have to be able to interact with the application.
This means that if somehow the components or the application contain, let's say, legacy interfaces,
it means that we would technically need to build some sort of wrapper or adapter
between all the components and all the applications involved.
So this would require an n-square number of wrappers and adapters to be implemented inside your distributor system.
So this would be the diagram on the net.
So this would be very hard to maintain, right?
To implement so many adapters and interfaces
that have to be maintained by programmers
will be very expensive.
I think even if you were to use AI,
you will burn through a lot of tokens
to be able to maintain them.
So it might not be really the best of solutions there.
Now, another solution would be to use a broker.
And this is a very typical solution in distributed systems.
So inside the middleware,
you implement a service that acts as a broker
between these legacy components.
So the legacy component, instead of communicating directly with the applications, with the legacy applications or components, they will actually communicate with the broker, and then the broker will implement an adapter or wrapper.
So this now allows you to reduce the number of wrappers and adapters that you need to implement to 2N, where N is the number of components, which makes it be more tractable.
Of course, you're adding some performance overhead, because now instead of having the applications be able to communicate directly with other applications, you have to use a broker, another system that sits in the middle, or a hub.
And then, of course, the broker could also pose challenges in terms of floor tolerance, right?
Because if the broker dies and the components, they cannot communicate with each other.
But of course, you can organize this broker system to be centralized at the logical level, but distributed at the physical level.
So you can have multiple machines actually implement the broker, which should only be the problem of fault tolerance.
So I want to make a small parenthesis because I know I mentioned, you know, you can use AI to maintain the code and everything, you know.
So I think, again, a lot of people, you know, talk about these days about, you know, AI and maybe replacing, you know, software engineers and, you know, let AI write the code for us.
And I just want to mention again that writing the code was never really the problem, I think, in software development.
The main problem has always been maintaining the code.
So how do you fix it?
How do you make the code work well in a specific context?
And then when it comes to distributed systems,
actually implementing these things has never really been the challenge.
The challenge has been how do we design a coherent system that works well.
So that's very difficult.
It depends on the context a lot.
So it depends on what application you need to implement.
With an AI, you need to give it a lot of information
to be able to replicate that kind of context
that a seasoned, let's say, software engineer would know already.
So this is where, even though these AI tools,
I think, again, the cat is out of the box,
so they're here.
We'll have to learn how to use them.
I don't think we know how to use them really well right now
because it's a very brand new technology.
If you think about it,
when the computers were introduced for the first time,
it took many years before people figured out
what to do with them.
I think it's kind of similar with AI.
Maybe we'll figure it out a little bit faster,
but right now we don't really know
the capabilities of these AI models.
We don't necessarily know exactly what they can do and what they cannot do.
So we're kind of learning how to operate with them.
But what's very important is that for you as a software engineer, what the AI cannot replace right now is the judgment part.
So you can judge by looking at an application, okay, am I going to implement these wrappers and adapters using an all-to-all implementation?
Then, of course, the AI will be happy to generate all of the code possible to make this work.
but it will become very hard to maintain, right,
and very expensive to maintain because for each interface,
you will burn through tokens, for example, versus using a broker.
And then even if you use a broker, you know,
depending on the situation, do you want to make the broker distributed?
Do you want to keep it as a single service?
Do you want to use some sort of mechanism where you select a new leader,
you know, that becomes a broker, for example, in your system?
There are a lot of solutions there.
But which one works better, it's very hard to determine
because you need a lot of information regarding the context.
So I'm hoping that in this class, by working on the assignments, you would be developing a little bit of judgment in terms of how you choose certain things inside your, let's say, application, inside the development of the application.
Okay?
So anyway, this is an example of, again, things that can look different in terms of architecture.
They can solve the same problem, but one might be better than the other depending on the situation.
Now, all right.
I'll close a parenthesis here.
now
what we assume
so far when we talk about these wrappers
and adapters is that we have access
to the code
of the components, especially
the legacy components, so we can modify
them so that they use these wrappers
and adapters between our system
and then we have access to our system
and we can implement those wrappers and adapters
on our side as well
so these wrappers and adapters have to be
implemented on both sides because maybe
the component wants to communicate with
our components inside a distributed system and our distributed system wants to communicate with
those legacy components as well. But a lot of the times we actually will not have access to the code
of the legacy component. So the legacy component might actually be a compiled program, right,
which means that we have access to the binary code. We can, you know, disassemble the code,
but this will not give us the actual code that was written in whatever programming languages was
written, right, which is get the assembly
instructions. So
sometimes it might be very hard to actually
modify that legacy
component in order to support these wrappers
and adapters. So then, to be able
to solve this problem
of developing, let's say,
adaptable middleware,
one of the solutions and one of the things that
the middleware can do is actually it can
intercept the
flow of control of a
specific application.
It can intercept the instructions
that are being executed, and it can transform them
into something else that is more appropriate
to whatever interface we have in the distributed system.
So this happens not just in distributed systems,
but it happens in operating systems as well.
I think as an example, I can give you the example
of what Apple and Microsoft have to do
when they decided that they wanted to support applications
and they built an operating system
that runs on the ARM architecture.
So one very important difference between the Apple, let's say,
silicon processors and the processors that we used to use
in the laptops and desktop computers
is that they use a completely different architecture.
So PC computers, they use the x86 architecture.
In the Internet, AMD, they produce processors
that follow the x86 architecture.
But Apple decided to move to ARM 64 for various reasons.
They had more control over their processors.
They could do an on-chip design, which then allowed them to make it more efficient, and so on and so forth.
But the most important aspect was that, since they had a completely different architecture,
they needed a completely different operating system, which they did.
They implemented, they re-implemented, they ported their operating system to the ARM64 architecture,
and they ported their applications as well.
But all of the applications that were not built by Apple, they had to be ported as well.
or if they were not ported, right,
Apple still wanted to give the users the ability to run them.
So what they did is they created this layer,
you can call it kind of like a middleware,
called Rosetta that can intercept x86 instructions
and convert them dynamically into ARM64 instructions.
Now, of course, it's not a very efficient way to do it, right,
but it allows you now to run applications
that were designed for one interface
on a completely different interface.
And Microsoft did the same thing.
I think their system, maybe it's called Prism,
but I don't remember exactly. But they have a similar system when you're running
x86 applications on Windows 11 for ARM, for example.
They also have a translation layer as well. So again,
the way this works is that you have some sort of hook inside your system
or inside the middleware that can capture different kind of calls or different kind of
instructions and then transform them dynamically into the
interface.
Okay. Any questions so far regarding logical architectures in the middleware?
I have a quick question just about why they made ARM64 you said?
Yes, yeah.
Was it because they were worried about patent law or something or it was just purely they wanted a different design?
They just wanted a different design so Apple has always been about having an integrated design.
So integrated means that they would like to tune the hardware.
They would like to tune the operating system.
They would like to tune the applications so that they all work together.
So the Apple ecosystem is actually very nice.
You can have a phone.
You can have a laptop and a desktop all from Apple, and they're all interconnected with each other.
So you can move tabs.
You can move applications from one from another.
You know, a tablet as well.
You know, you can do all these fancy things.
And I think Apple really wanted to build, again, computers.
Well, there were two reasons there.
They wanted to build computers that were power efficient,
so a laptop that can actually last for 24 hours, right?
The PC world, they said, oh, you cannot build that because of power constraints and whatever, you know.
They put all of these reasons.
So Apple said, okay, we'll design a home processor.
what they did is they've integrated the processor with the memory and with the system bus.
So that's why on an Apple computer, everything is soldered directly to the motherboard.
So you cannot upgrade anymore, your processor, your RAM, everything is soldered.
But because it's soldered, they can control the signals.
Because they soldered the RAM, they were able to use low power DDR RAM instead of the regular RAM.
So they were able to, you know, save a lot of energy.
It's not necessarily that the ARM64 architecture has an inherent advantage over the x86.
And the differences are not really that big.
But it has more to do with the fact that the ARM architecture is a clean architecture.
Apple, they now have to provide backwards compatibility inside their architecture.
You know, x86 or other architectures.
And then they were able to optimize the communication paths on the chip.
So that things are very efficient.
They use, you know, low energy, you know, or they have a very good performance per watt, let's say, performance.
So that's one of the reasons.
They wanted to build something that, again, lasted for 24 hours.
But then again, they also built the Mac Studios, right, which then they don't have a battery.
Right.
So then the other reason why they built this system is because they wanted to build systems that, I think,
that were suited for the AI workloads that they anticipated.
I think Apple, you know, had some breath in the mind there.
I think they anticipated that, okay, so LLMs are becoming a thing,
AI is becoming a thing.
I think a lot of people will want to run local models on their computers.
So what would be the best way for us to build computers
that have a lot of RAM that is also very fast,
that people would buy to run models on?
So that's where they, I wouldn't say that they innovated because those architectures existed in supercomputers as well, but they adopted and they chose their architectures in order to satisfy this AI workload.
So what's also very unique about Apple is how they view the unified memories,
the unified between processor and GPU.
So in Apple, the processor and the GPU can actually access the exact same physical memory,
of course, at different speeds, but without any translation between applications.
Now, the way, for example, a process in a PC computer or a laptop
accesses the memory of a GPU
is you have to actually create a clone
of the memory. So
the memory of the GPU, right, the GPU
has its own dedicated memory,
but it has to be mapped to the physical
memory. So you're storing stuff
in the physical memory and then
using GPU
instructions to transfer memory from the
memory to the GPU to then
do the operations on the GPU.
On the Apple computer, because they had
control over the architecture, they were able
to design a chip where the GPU can
access the main memory directly no translation needed no transfers needed this is their innovation
which was actually done very well and from that point of view the apple computers are superior
especially for ai workloads anyways amd and intel tried to replicate that nvidia tried to replicate
that right by creating unified architectures but they're not really unified so with the
AMD Ryzen AI Max Plus whatever the name is right for the long name of chip that they have.
They also sell with 120 gigabytes of RAM that can also be used for the GPU.
Keep in mind that there's still some copying that happens.
It's not a pure unified memory architecture.
And then for NVIDIA's DGX SparkBox that also doesn't have a pure unified memory
because the GPU has a bunch of memory and then the rest of the ARM processor
so it has a bunch of memory, and they operate at different speeds.
So you have to be aware on how you transfer the data.
The CUDA library can transfer the data for you, can try to detect,
but you can also do manual transfer of data as well
to make your application be a bit more efficient.
So anyways, in the end, that was the reason why they switched to this ARM
so that they can have full control.
But I think they predicted that that's the kind of stuff that people would use,
so they wanted to be the first ones in the market that had computers for that,
So, which, I think in the end, they ended up being correct.
All right, any other questions?
All right.
Well, if there are no other questions, then let's start talking about how do we organize
distributed systems from a physical point of view.
We'll talk about the physical architectures.
And before we talk actual distributed architectures, I think it's very important to
understand centralized system architectures and more specifically the
client server model. So this is a very popular model I kind of want to say that
a great very great majority of applications that exist in the cloud in
the web or phones you know they follow this client server model it's actually
very simple model to understand and to use and then from this model we actually
we can derive more complex distributor systems models.
So the client-server model has a few characteristics.
It's, again, very easy to understand.
What we do is we organize a client-server system into processes.
The processes can have one of two roles.
The processes can be clients or they can act as servers.
The servers, they offer services.
So they have computational functions, resources, right?
That the clients can access.
So the clients, they usually make use of those services provided by the servers.
The clients and the servers can be deployed on different machines.
They can be co-located, but they can also run on different machines.
And then the most important property is that the clients,
they follow a request-reply model regarding using the services.
So whenever a client wants to use a service from a server, it needs to submit a request.
It sends that request to some sort of communication mechanism.
The server receives it.
The server then processes the response and then sends back the response using the same communication mechanism.
So here in this diagram, you can see that we have a process which represents the client and a process which represents the server.
If the client wants to make use of a service provided by the server, he sends a request,
he then waits for the server to process the reply,
and then the server will send back the response or the reply to the client.
Okay, this is the most easy way to understand client-server model.
Again, it exists everywhere.
When you're using your application, when you're using Gmail or Outlook to access your email,
basically your Outlook application acts as a client,
and then it connects to a server in Microsoft to receive the email.
Very simple.
When you go to YouTube and you request a video, client-server model.
You're sending a request, you're receiving the email.
Okay, very good.
Now, let's see how do we integrate these logical architectures
that we talked about last week with this physical way of organizing
a centralized system or a distributed system.
So let's start with the application layering architecture.
So if you remember, application layering, it's a layered architecture where you split your application to three layers.
One layer is responsible with managing the user interface, another layer for processing, and another layer for the data.
now of course
you can for example
still implement
a let's say client server
application where
the entire user interface
and the entire processing layer and the entire
data layer resides on the server
so then the client
basically connects to the server
through some sort of other protocol and then
runs the application on the server
so this is called a single tiered
architecture where
basically the client
connects to some sort of terminal interface
to the server. So let's say
for example that I want to
ask you after you implement programming
assignment 2 and you build the search engine
I would
tell you that hey I want to run
this search engine on
Chameleon Cloud but then I'd like for you
to be able to connect to that server
you know file retrieval engine
from Chameleon Cloud I'd like you to be able to connect
from your laptop and your desktop computer
let's see. The easiest way that you would connect and run the application
is by SSH-ing into that machine and running the application
directly from that machine. This is an example of a single-tiered architecture.
There's nothing that happens that gets processed on the client side. You just connect
to a terminal to the server and you're accessing the resources on the server or you're accessing
the application. Now, of course, we can also
create a two-tier
literature, where now we split part of the application
and we'll put one part of the application on the client and one part of the application
on the server. Now keep in mind that the application is organized in layers.
So the question is, how do we split these layers between the client
machine and the server machine? The diagrams that we have here on the bottom
represents the various ways you can split those layers.
So in diagram A, you can split, for example,
part of the user interface can be executed on the client.
The remaining user interface, application layer and data layer
can be implemented on the server.
You can have the entire user interface running on the client in diagram B,
and then the processing layer and the data layer be executed on the server side.
You can split the application layer.
You can split the data layer as well.
Okay, so let's give some examples of all of these ways of configuring a two-tiered architecture.
So whenever you hear web applications, right, so websites,
they can be implemented or they're usually implemented
by either following configuration from diagram B or from diagram C.
I kind of want to say that 26 years ago,
websites were implemented following the configurations from diagram B.
Basically, the user interface was computed on the client.
So this would be your web browser.
Your web browser will receive the HTML page and will render the HTML page on your computer.
So the user interface part was solely done on the client machine.
And then in the server, you have the backend that took care of the logic of your website,
and the database that stored your data related to your website.
Nowadays, modern-day web applications actually fall into the category of diagram C
because a part of the application from the server gets actually sent to the browser
under the form of JavaScript code.
They can actually run code in your browser
and do certain kinds of operations that are part of the processing layer.
And then the server will still do its own processing,
and the data resides always on the servers.
Now, let's see if we can look at other configurations.
So, let's see at configuration A.
I think the best example that I can give you is the attempt that Google tried to make
to build a gaming-as-a-service platform.
So, again, if you play video games, you might have heard that Google was trying to build
a cloud that allowed you to actually play a game in the cloud.
So, for example, you could play it from any computer, right?
If your computer didn't have a lot of computational power to render the game,
rendering would be done on the server,
the logic of the game would be done on the server,
and then the game itself, the files of the game,
would be stored on the server.
So if you look at Configuration A,
this is how we would describe that two-tiered architecture
that Google tried to build.
Part of the user interface would be processed on your machine.
The rest of the user interface, which is the rendering,
probably, of the beta game, will be processed on the server,
The logic of the game is on the cloud, you know, in Google, and then the data for the game is also in the cloud as well.
Can Google Drive be an example of a Google Drive?
Yeah, so Google Drive, let's see, so Google Drive, it's a bit more simplistic because Google Drive itself doesn't really have a very fancy interface.
We're typically accessing it using a web browser, right, and it just manages the data.
So the processing layer is not very sophisticated.
You cannot really do sophisticated processing
inside Google Drive.
So I would say it still falls in the area of B or C.
Mostly B because, again, the application,
Google Drive doesn't really run JavaScript
on your browser, I think.
I think they do some operations to cache data,
but not really to process data.
It could also fall in the category of B
if you eliminate the application,
where maybe part of the data gets cached on your browser,
but then the rest of the data resides in your cloud.
So, for example, for configuration E,
another example that is similar is when you do software development.
So, let's say you do software development on your local app.
The way this would work is you would open some sort of code editor or IDE.
It has a user interface.
It has a processing layer where you have the compilers and analyzers for code.
And what you do is you do a git clone to clone the data on your computer.
So store a copy of the data on your computer, you process it,
and then you resynchronize your data with the data on the server.
So GitHub stores only your code,
but doesn't really run any part of your ID
or any part of the process.
It could run nowadays with continuous integration,
continuous development systems,
but let's say the old school way, it would not.
So that's where you have the data,
is now split between the client and the server, they both store different parts.
And then you can also have applications where the user interface and the processing all
happens on the client side and then the data resides on the database side.
So let's say, for example, if you want to access a database on a different machine,
an SQL database, for example, if it's a Postgres database, you can use pgadmin.
So, pgAdmin is an application, right?
That you can run locally.
It's a client application.
So, it runs the UI there,
and you can do some partial processing inside the UI.
Well, it actually kind of falls more
into the category of a diagram C
because you can do partial processing
on the client as well.
Where you think?
Does the system be deep
where it's like you have the game
And then what you did in the game is from the database and it updates.
Yeah, you can do a multiplayer game where that runs on the server,
where the data is on the server, but then the processing layer
and the user interface gets processed on your machine.
Yeah, that's true.
So that's actually a very good example.
Yeah, a very good example.
I didn't think about it, but yeah, that's a very good example of an application
because the data resides on the server.
The server sometimes might do some processing there,
so you'll be aware it might be, you know, Diagram C as well but you know,
you could have the data stored directly on the server and then all the logic
it's completely on the product. Okay, all right, very good. Now of course you can
split the application layer in a three-tier architecture as well where you
put in either each layer or subsets of the layers on three different machines
and you can go, of course you can create an n-tiered architecture if you wanted to.
So this way of, you know, let's say, organizing a layered architecture using the client-server model can be applied to, of course, other layered architectures, not just the application layering architecture.
But the most important thing that we have to remember is that if you have a layered architecture, where, again, in order for layer one to do its operation is to call functions from layer two, which is to, you know, use services from layer three and so on and so forth.
just keep in mind that the wait time will increase.
So for example, let's say that we have a client machine
that wants to communicate with some sort of server here
that needs to communicate with a data server.
Right.
So when the client sends a request,
the client machine acts as a client
while the server acts as a server
and receives the request.
But the server also has to act as a client
and send a request to the data server,
which then the data server needs to send a response
and then after the processing server receives the response
it needs to send the response back to the client
which means that the client needs to wait for that entire wait time.
So the deeper the tiered architecture is
the more you'll probably need to wait.
The more the client will need to wait for all those requests to go through.
But as you can see it's an easy way to organize an application.
And by using the client-server model, you cannot deploy it across multiple machines as well.
Of course, this can be applied to the service-oriented model as well,
where you're sending the request for different objects.
It doesn't have to be necessary only for the layered architecture.
Now, let's look at some other properties of client-server models,
especially when it comes to the sharing of resources.
More specifically, the sharing of data, let's say, under the form of files.
So, again, just knowing that you can send these requests and these responses,
it's not usually enough to be able to reason about how do you organize an application, a distributed application.
So, when it comes to the sharing of data, and more specifically the sharing of files,
people have identified actually two kinds of access models for accessing that data.
You can use an upload-download model, or you can use a remote access model for accessing the data.
Now, let's see what the difference between them are.
Let's see, again, you have a client and a server.
Now, let's look first at the diagram on the right at the upload-download model.
So, in the upload-download model, if a client machine wants to access a file from the server,
what the client needs to do is to send a request to the server.
The server needs to transfer the file to the client.
The client will then need to do operations on the file locally, and then it will need to send back that file to the server.
Now, why do we need to do this?
Let's take a look at the example of how we do file operations on a Unix slash Linux-based system.
So does anyone remember what are the four main operations or system calls that you need to use in order to interact with files on a Linux slash Unix basis?
I'm sure you've heard about them.
If you know the system calls, then you can implement more advanced libraries for reading and writing data.
You can do very fancy stuff.
But you're always going to use at least these four functions.
You have to open the file?
Open the file, right?
So you have to open the file, you can then read and write to the file,
and then you have to close the file.
These are the four operations, right?
So if I want to build a system, right,
that allows me to access files from a server, right,
and if the system is a very good distributed system,
it means it has good transparency.
It means that I shouldn't have to modify my program to tell it to,
hey, download this file, modify it, and then download it back.
It should be pretty transparent, right?
So I should be able to use the exact same program
and it should work. Well, systems similar to Dropbox
or the File Transfer Protocol, that's what they attempt to do.
So with Dropbox or OneDrive or Google Drive, when you download
the client program in your computer, it tries to act as a
distributed system that manages your files in the cloud and it synchronizes your
files with your computer. But Dropbox uses this upload-download
model. So whenever you want to edit a file or read
the file from Drawbox, it needs to transfer
the file from the cloud.
If you read it, then that's fine. You don't have to do anything
special about it. But if you modify
it, you modify it locally using the
regular system calls, and
then the client program will automatically
synchronize the file back to the cloud.
Alright, now another way
that you can implement this, if you want
to have even better transparency
and if you want to avoid certain
let's say performance products,
is you can implement
the remote access model. So for the remote access model, I still have
the situation where a client wants to access the data
of a file that resides on a different server. But now instead of transferring
the file from the server to the client and then back from the client to the server,
what I'm going to do is I'm actually going to transfer the computation
from the client to the server. So now whenever the client wants to do an
open system call, a closed system call, or read or write,
Those operations will now actually be forwarded from the client to the server.
So if I want to modify, let's say, 100 megabytes in a 4-gigabyte file,
I want to modify maybe somewhere in the middle, right?
I just need to send that operation, send 100 bytes of data,
and then the operation will actually happen on the server side.
So we can already see one advantage of the remote access model, right,
is that I don't have to transfer the entire data to do an operation on that data.
The disadvantage is that I don't have any duplicates of the data on the client machine.
So the client actually does not store that data in any form whatsoever.
Maybe parts of the data might reside in RAM,
in some sort of buffers when I do these operations.
But whenever I close the file,
the file will reside on the server, not on the client.
So for a very large file, if I just need to modify 100 megabytes,
a 4 gigabyte file with the upload download model, I've got to transfer
4 gigabytes, modify 100 megabytes, and then transfer the data back.
That's a lot of data that needs to be transferred back and forth.
With the remote access, I just need to send that operation,
the right operation, to the server and perform that operation directly on the server.
So there is a system that implements the remote access model.
It is still very popular
in units-based and Linux-based systems.
It used to be the main file system for supercomputers 30 years ago.
Now they use a parallel or distributed file system,
which is kind of a network file system that can store the data on multiple servers simultaneously.
But the network file system, or NFS, is a very popular solution for implementing, again,
file sharing between a server and multiple clients.
The way the network file system works is you run some programs, both on the client side
and on the server side, and they transform those operations for you.
We say that the client machines will mount folders or files from the server machine,
so they get attached to the file system structure, and they appear to the user as if they are
normal files, but whenever we access them, the operations happen on the server.
Now, how does the network file system implement this?
It implements it actually through the use of a layer or a middleware layer that is actually provided by the operating system.
So modern-day Unix and Linux-based systems, what they do is they implement a layer called the virtual file system layer, or VFS.
So this means that any single time your program does a system call to operate on files, the system call gets captured by the operating system and gets sent to the virtual file system layer library.
The virtual file system layer library then makes a choice, depending if the file resides, for example, locally on your machine, it will forward that operation to the local file system interface, which will then be able to do those operations directly on the file that is stored locally.
If you're doing this operation over a file or a directory that is mounted from a server,
so it resides on a remote machine,
then the virtual file system layer will do a call to the network file system client program.
And then the client program will use some sort of communication mechanism.
Let's say the original network file system implementation used a remote procedure call.
So it would do a remote procedure call to a server stop, which will then forward the operation to the network file system server.
And then the network file system server will forward the operation to the virtual file system layer of the server machine, which will then make that decision again.
And since the file resides locally on the server machine, it will actually forward that operation to the local file system interface of the server.
It means to return any data, right?
When you do a read operation, you get, you know, the contents of the data that you read
plus the amount of data that you read.
When you write operation, you get the amount of bytes that you wrote to the file.
So you get back that information to the callback of that remote procedure call
of that message that was being sent.
But basically, it works in a request-reply fashion.
So the network fire system client sends a request to the server,
he performs the approbation, and then he gives back a reply.
every single time.
That's how the read, write, open, close functions work.
There's always some sort of return
that you get back from.
Okay, now one small parenthesis here.
I don't know if I mentioned last time
regarding drawbox.
This is more of a historical take.
Again, let me know if I said it or not,
but basically,
regarding how drawbox used to run
initially when it was initially created,
Believe it or not, that Dropbox was basically a wrapper on top of Amazon S3 storage.
So Amazon built this object storage in the cloud.
So Dropbox came and they built a web interface on top of it.
But they were storing everything in S3.
And they were just charging a few more cents than Amazon S3 did.
And that's how they made their money.
Only later on, once they needed to scale more and the prices weren't favorable anymore,
where they decide to build their own way of organizing the objects inside the distributed system.
But at the beginning, Dropbox was just a wrapper on top of Amazon S3.
So, very interesting way to make money.
Very easy.
All right.
Now, as other examples of client-server applications,
of course, the de facto example is the example of web servers.
And here it's worth noting that web servers have changed over time.
So again, 26 years ago, web servers followed a two-tier architecture
where you had a client machine and a server machine.
The client ran the browser, the server ran the web server.
Typically, the web server was co-located with the database,
so you would access the database directly.
And whenever, for example, your browser would request a web page,
it would send the request to the server,
the server would have the web pages statically stored somewhere on the file or in the database.
and we'll basically grab that HTML file, maybe with CSS, you know, stylization component,
send it back to the browser, and then the browser will render.
So very simple architecture.
Nowadays, web servers and web applications are implemented differently.
So the web pages are not stored statically on disk or a database.
They're actually generated dynamically.
And it makes sense because modern-day web applications are very complex.
They sometimes require various kinds of data that you have to include in your web page.
is dynamic data. So the best way would be to try to generate that data dynamically.
So it's very common nowadays when it comes to the deployment of web servers to see multi-tiered
architecture. So here is an example of a four-tier architecture. There's a box missing here. This
would be the client. So the client will still send the request to a web server, but the web
server does not serve the page directly now anymore. The web server actually forwards the
request to a program called a CGI program or common gateway interface.
You might hear the name of this gateway interface differently in practice.
You know, if you do web development you might hear SGI synchronous gateway interface, ASGIA
synchronous gateway interface, of course there are various advantages and events for using
them.
But in principle, they're all a process that will generate a webpage dynamic.
And then the CGI programs might also sometimes send requests to a database that might result
on a different machine to actually retrieve some parts of the data.
So, this, again, makes sense if, let's say, you know, you're building the Amazon Web Store
at the beginning, right, and you have a lot of information that you have to print in different
formats depending on different locations, right, in the world or in different states,
right, so you need to be able to access that data in a dynamic way.
You might have multiple databases with multiple products, right?
So you don't want to create only one web page, static web page, and then include that information
there and then try to filter it out.
What you want to do is you want to generate the web pages dynamically, depending on whatever
the user wants to see, whatever user is searching, whatever they have in their card, so on and
so forth.
So it makes sense to have, again, the CGI programs that can then accommodate that kind
of dynamic behavior.
So the CGI program will then compile and generate an HTML page, and it will send that HTML page to the web server, which will then forward it back to the client.
Okay.
All right.
Now, let's take a look at how do we move now from the centralized client-server model to something that will be more distributed, right?
And there are various ways we can distribute these services, as we've seen so far.
So there are two strategies when it comes to, let's say, if you have a layered architecture or a service-oriented architecture,
you can distribute those components either by following a vertical distribution strategy or a horizontal distribution strategy.
So vertical distribution strategy means that, and I'm so sorry, I keep on pressing here on the top of the screen,
and for some reason it makes the screen not highlighted,
but like gray sort of, and I don't know why.
Anyways, so vertical distribution means that
if I have some sort of distributed application,
let's say organized in multiple layers,
in this example is three logical layers,
what I can do to make this application more distributed
is I can actually run each layer on a separate machine.
Why, if I have n layers, I can use n machines
and I can run each layer on a separate machine.
And that way, I built a distributed system.
Another way would be to use the horizontal distribution strategy,
which means that if I have multiple layers,
instead of putting one layer on a single machine,
maybe a layer is more demanding.
I split that layer into two, again, cloned layers,
or very similar layers, and I run them on different machines.
Now, each of these layers, they have access to a separate portion of the entire data.
So there's no overlap in terms of functional responsibility between those two layers.
They implement the same functions, but they operate on different data sets altogether.
So that's one way to, again, build another distributed system.
Now, I do want to make a parenthesis here.
When people talk about distributed systems, you will also hear the notion of vertical scalability and horizontal scalability.
So that actually refers to something else.
So when you have, let's say, an application, right,
and they say, okay, does your application scale vertically
or does it scale horizontally?
What it refers to is does your application,
does the performance of your application increase?
Performance came in like how many requests per second you can process, right?
Does it increase vertically if you add more cores, more RAM,
more hard drives inside one single computer?
So that's vertical scalability.
So on one single computer, you add more resources.
Does your application run past?
Horizontal scalability means if I add more computers,
does the application increase in performance?
Okay, so when it comes to the organization of distributed systems,
how do you distribute the layers of a distributed system
refers to this vertical distribution versus horizontal distribution.
Okay, keep in mind, again, these are differences between.
All right. So again, you can split the logical layers.
Or another way to organize a distributed system is by following, let's say, a peer-to-peer architecture approach.
So in a peer-to-peer architecture approach, all of the components or processes that are in the system,
we design them in a way where they act as both clients and servers at the same time.
So all of the processes are both clients and servers,
and they can contact any other process either as a client
or be contacted as a server by any other process.
This is the most important property of these peer-to-peer architectures.
This is, again, very distributed.
All of the components, they have the same role inside the distributed system.
so when it comes to
peer-to-peer systems there are of course
two ways or two kinds of peer-to-peer systems out there
so you can have structured peer-to-peer systems or unstructured
peer-to-peer systems. Structured means that those
again processes that act both as clients and servers
they are organized in a predictable way or there is some sort of
structure that they found.
The unstructured means that they connect at will and each component will have different
neighbors and, you know, different number of neighbors at any moment of time.
They can come in, they can leave, and there is no particular structure in the way that
they're organized.
Now, let's look first at structured peer-to-peer networks.
These are more easy to work with and they're more, let's say, popular out there.
So one important challenge when it comes to implementing peer-to-peer systems actually has to do with how do you identify data inside a peer-to-peer system.
In a client-server architecture, it's very easy to identify where the data is.
The client can ask the server, the server can tell the client, hey, this is where the data is, or this client has the data, or I have the data.
So we access a centralized entity that will tell us where the information is.
But in a peer-to-peer system where any component can act,
both as client and as server, we don't know exactly where the data is,
especially if we want to implement some sort of data sharing,
let's say peer-to-peer system.
So what this means is that we need to build some sort of mechanisms
to determine who has a piece of data.
If you think about it, this is what Google did
when they designed their Google search engine.
they were trying to solve the problem of having these many servers and many clients out there
that were trying to search for data, and they were trying to find out which of the servers out there,
which of the web servers out there contain a piece of information.
So they build an index for it.
Now, the index can be built in two ways.
So for structured peer-to-peer networks, because the peer-to-peer system is organized in a predictable way,
we can actually build what's called a semantic free index.
So let's look first at what does it mean to have a structured peer-to-peer system.
So again, we can organize them.
We have an example here.
We can organize the, let's say, nodes or the processes in that system in a predictable way.
So we can explore various kinds of graph or geometrical shapes to actually implement by the topology of the processes or of the nodes.
And whenever we create
this geometry or
graph space
that is again symmetrical
or in a predictable way, we can also
assign unique identifiers
to all of the
nodes out of the
peer-to-peer system. If they are
unstructured, it's very hard because
we don't have a centralized way of assigning
the nodes. But when it's structured,
we have a way of assigning the nodes.
So for the example of the
hypercube let's say topology we have 16 nodes we can organize them in a hypercube configuration
where basically each node has four neighbors or has four immediate immediate neighbors
but they're all interconnected in a way where if a node wants to send the data to another node that
is not a neighbor it can forward the data to one of the neighbors and then the other neighbor can
forward it and send it to the proper node.
Now also, interestingly here, in a hybrid configuration, since this is a cube in four
dimensions, the way I can structure these nodes is I can give them different coordinates
in that 4D space.
So for example, the identification numbers that you see here for each node represents
the base, let's say, vector or coordination in that 4D space.
So for example, identifier 0000 means that the node resides at the center of the four-dimensional axis, right?
Let's say if I have 0001, it means that it has, it's the vector with one unit in that four-dimensional space, right, on the x-axis, right?
And I can arrange all of these points to create this, again, hypercube.
You can also do a 3D cube if you have a smaller number of nodes, depending on how many neighbors we have.
So now, because you can create these unique identifiers, and because you have a structure,
you know how to forward the data between the nodes.
It makes it very easy if you need to route requests, which also means that if you need to figure out a way
how do you organize the data in the system so you can easily find this data,
You can then use, of course, a hash function.
So again, the semantic free index means that we can decide how do we organize the data in the system without knowing details about the contents of the data.
And we do this by using a hash function.
If you remember, the hash function, we see there's an input, a variable-sized input, and it returned a fixed-size output.
But it didn't matter what I placed as an input.
It could be binary data, it could be human-reliable data, it could be another number.
It doesn't really matter.
So whenever I want to store data inside the system, what I do is for each piece of data,
I also have a key as well, right?
And then for that key, I can apply a hash function, which will give me some sort of number.
If I apply a module operation over the number to determine, you know, in which of these nodes the system will go,
so I can do a module operation where I extract, let's say, you know, the last or the first four bits of that, you know,
generated hash function number.
and then by using the number I can determine which node is responsible
for the piece of data that has key, let's say, k.
So I store the data, right, now in this system, right,
I store the data in the nodes that are responsible for managing the specific, let's say, key space.
Now if I need to search for a piece of data by using the key,
what I do is I calculate, right, I use the hash function to calculate, you know,
which node is responsible for that data and then I send the request to that specific node.
So even though all the nodes act both as clients and servers,
I can still identify where the data is by building this semantic free index
by exploiting the structure of the peer-to-peer network.
Now, of course, this also has limitations,
because so far we talked about a static, let's say, topology for this peer-to-peer network.
So the number of nodes and the way that they are connected doesn't really change.
But what happens if we want to remove a node or we want to add a new node?
If we add a new node, we probably need to reconfigure the entire architecture, which means that probably the identification numbers for all of the nodes change or the increase in numbers.
So now instead of using 4 bits, I have to use 5 bits, which means that now I have to reorganize the data and send it to the proper node because now I'm doing a modulo.
Instead of, you know, the first 4 bits, I'm doing the first 5 bits instead.
So I need to completely reorganize the data, which is not very efficient.
So this problem, however, has been solved.
So the DIM solutions, I think the Chord solution has been proposed, I think, in the early 2000s.
So again, 26 years ago, people have figured out how to build a structure, peer-to-peer systems,
where nodes can join and can leave as well.
The way that they build this is by creating a virtual keyspace.
And we're just going to discuss it again conceptually.
You don't have to understand how the church system works for the exam.
This will be the topic for the Distributed Systems 2 class if you want to build one of these.
Or just let me know offline, and I'll give you more resources on how to build it.
But what's important here is that they use this notion of the key space, or a virtual key space,
and then assigning nodes to various key spaces and making them responsible for one or more key spaces.
So the way that the short system works is you have to, of course, organize the nodes and give each node an mbit identifier, which data item is hashed to an mbit key.
The data item with tk is stored at a node with the smallest identifier, and then the read is extended with various shortcuts.
So basically, whenever you create a short system, you create first a key space.
You want the keyspace to actually be larger than the number of nodes that you expect that will be part of this tracked system.
So in this case, they selected the keyspace of 32 keys.
So that would be 5 bits.
So they used 5 bits to create a keyspace, right?
You can have 32 unique keys.
2 to the power of 5 is 32 elements, so 32 unique keys.
So a piece of data can be placed in any of these keyspaces.
These are, again, are virtual keyspaces.
Now, whenever a node joins the CHUR network,
they will be assigned an identifier.
The identifier is the same as the keyspace.
And the node will then be responsible
to manage all of the keys that are stored
in all of the key spaces
that are less or equal than the identifier until they reach a new node.
So for example here, let's say that I have, in this diagram,
so the dotted line represents a key space.
The full line or full circle represents a node
that is also managing the key space with that same number.
So in this case, let's say that I have node number 9.
Node number 9 is responsible for managing all of the data
that goes into key space nine, eight, seven, six, and five.
For example, node number four is responsible
for all of the data that falls into key space four, three, and two,
and so on and so forth, right?
So it means that when I want to insert a piece of data in the system,
I have to calculate the hash function,
and I have to see which node is responsible with managing that data.
Again, in this system, the nodes are also the client,
So they're the ones who are initiating these operations to figure out where do I store the data.
If I want to do a lookup for the data, let's say that, you know, in this example, they do a lookup from node 9,
and they're searching for a piece of data that has, let's say, the hash function applied over the key is key 3,
so the data will be in key space number 3.
We know that key space number 3 is managed by node 4, right?
So again, there are a few shortcuts that get created and there is a specific rule on how you create the shortcuts in the charge system.
But here, and then after you create the shortcuts, the rule is that you want to go to the highest node that can manage that key.
So in this case, node number nine will forward request to node 28 because that's the highest number that can maybe manage their key.
Then from here, from 28, it jumps to node 1 and it jumps to node 4.
And then node 4 is the one that manages key space 2.
So again, by using the shortcuts, you can find the data.
Now, the beauty of this system is that you can add new nodes without having to reorganize the entire data.
So let's say that I add a new node and the new node maybe receives identifier 7,
which means that now the node has to be responsible for the keys 7, 6, and 5.
So when the new node gets added, the shortcuts get updated.
And then node number 7 will let its successor know that,
hey, I'm going to be managing from now on all of the keys in key space 7, 6, and 5.
So node number 9 will just transfer the data from key space 7, 6, and 5.
And then node number 9 will only be responsible with key spaces 9 in.
right so this is a better way to reorganize the data we have without having to reconvert you know
and we transfer all the data between all of the nodes we just transfer the data between the two
nodes if for example in the seem architecture node number nine wants to live it needs to contact
its successor and say hey i am going to leave here is all of the key spaces that i manage all of the
data from the key spaces that i manage you're now responsible with managing these key spaces
So, we're just transferring the data from 9 to 11, and 11 will then manage all of the data.
So, again, examples on how you can build structured peer-to-peer networks.
So, again, this example is old.
However, this example is a precursor of a more modern technique that people use
to organize data in a distributed system, especially with structured peer-to-peer networks.
So, the most popular solution is a distributed hash table.
Because this kind of works like a hash table where you have a key space and you're hashing the data and you're placing it in a specific bucket.
And you make certain nodes be responsible for certain buckets.
Now, how do you determine which node is responsible for which bucket?
Well, you create another hash table.
So you have a hierarchical hash table.
The first hash table tells you which node manages the data.
and then the second hash table tells you
in which part of that node you can find the data
or in which button you can find the data.
And this again has an extra hub,
but there's also another kind of data structure out there
that can help you build these peer-to-peer systems,
which is called a zero-hub distributed hash table.
And that's the most recent, let's say, discovery
when it comes to organizing peer-to-peer argumentators.
All right.
But what happens if you cannot structure a peer-to-peer architecture?
That can happen when you build a peer-to-peer system over the Internet.
There's no guarantee that you can build it in a structured way.
Usually structured peer-to-peer networks, they're still built in a tightly clustered system
or tightly connected system that you have control over.
You can build some sort of topology.
So for unstructured peer-to-peer networks,
unfortunately we are at the mercy of just when we need to search for a piece of data,
we are at the mercy of flooding the network with messages to see whoever has that piece of data.
So this strategy, again, is for flooding.
Basically, when you need to search for a piece of data, you send a request to all of your neighbors.
The neighbors also send a request to their neighbors,
and you just end up flooding the network in order to be able to find the resource.
This is not very efficient, especially from a network bandwidth point of view.
If everyone wants to search, the entire network will be flooded with messages.
It's not very efficient.
One important property is whenever you send these messages, you have to also put a time-to-live, let's say, parameter program,
so that they don't stay there in the network indefinitely.
The data cannot be found.
You want to be able at some point for them to just die, which means you might never receive an answer.
So another solution, especially for unstructured 3D networks where the data is replicated so there are many copies of the data, you can also do a random walk.
So a random walk means that you're sending that search message to a subset of your neighbors and then they forward that message to a subset of their neighbors.
And at some point, since the data is replicated, you will hit it at some point.
There's a higher chance of you.
However, the practical way that people solve this problem of finding resources in unstructured
peer-to-peer networks is to actually build a superpeer network.
So a superpeer network, in a superpeer network, you still have a bunch of peers that are organized
in an unstructured way.
We'll call these peers weak peers.
And then on top of these weak peers, we can then assign or we can build a set of superpeers.
Now, the weak peers, they are organized in a, again, unstructured way.
As long as a weak peer can connect to one super peer, then it can function inside the network.
Even if it doesn't connect directly to the super peer, it can still function.
Now, the super peers are typically organized in a structured way.
And they create what's called an overlay network.
So they are organized in a structured way.
And these super peers, they act as indexing servers for the data that is stored in this super peer network.
The data resides actually on the weaker peers.
But the weaker peers, they communicate with the super peer, and the super peer collects an index of the data.
Imagine that you were to take your application to the next level in programming assignment 2.
And let's say that you want to implement an application that allows you to index data not only on your computer,
but across on every student's computer in this class, right?
We can implement it in two ways.
We can build a centralized server
where we build the index
and everyone will upload their files
or index their files and update it in the server,
or we can implement it in a peer-to-peer fashion
where everyone, right,
stores a local copy of the index.
Now, there are two ways we can do this.
We can do it structurally
where we assign unique identifiers
all of the computers
and then move the data
that belongs to one identifier or key space
on the different computers, or we can do it in an unstructured way
where you have to communicate with each other.
Ideally, what you would like to do is you would like to have
a few of the colleagues act as superpeers that you can contact
to find where the data is.
This is how the superpeer network works.
Now, let's see an example of a system that implements
a superpeer network.
And, of course, we go back to the BitTorrent things.
And I've already mentioned right before that the BitTorrent protocol
in order to overcome the problems of this asymmetry that we have on the internet.
The fact that we can download at fast speed, but we can upload them at most speeds.
So to be able to download data from other peers without using a data center or a server,
it would be better to split the data into multiple chunks and then download it from multiple people.
That way, if we download a chunk at 20 megabits per second,
if I download five chunks from five different people, I can get 100 megabits per second downloaded.
Okay, so that was the main problem that they were trying to solve.
Now, the BitTorrent protocol, it's organized as a super-peer architecture.
So the nodes, or the weak peers, are the nodes that contain the actual data.
The data gets split into multiple chunks.
Now, the super-peers are named trackers in the BitTorrent protocol.
So a tracker is another server that keeps track of the peers
and what kind of data they have.
Now what a tracker can do, a tracker can be added to a file called a torrent file.
A torrent file, basically, it's another type of index
where according to the data that you're looking for,
it will tell you which trackers might have that data.
Okay, so let's say if you're running the BitTorrent,
you know, client or program on your computer, if you want to download
a piece of data, you would first need to go and access
a web server to find the trackers
that can help you download that data. So the web server, from the web
server, you typically download some sort of torrent file. The torrent file will have a
number of trackers.
After you extract the trackers, your
BitTorrent program will contact the trackers and
will try to join the swarm as long as the data resides there.
So in the BitTorrent protocol, in order to be able to download
a piece of data, you have to join a swarm of nodes.
Those nodes create a swarm when they want to share
the same piece of data.
So when you join the swarm for the first time,
the swarm will give you a few chunks of data for free.
So the BitTorrent protocol tried to also solve the problem
of people who would abuse the system,
who would only want to download
but not share data, right?
In order for the system to work well,
people have to, you know,
their systems have to be able
to share data
but also download data at the same time.
So in order to balance that out,
inside a swarm,
when you want to download
the piece of data,
you receive a few chunks for free,
but then to download more chunks,
you have to share your chunks as well.
So you can only download once,
you know, other people
want that data as well.
So once you join the swarm, again, you get a few chunks,
and then you start sharing and downloading out of chunks until you have your company there.
If you ever used the BitTorrent programs before,
you might have noticed sometimes that you would download a file and it would stop like 80%.
It doesn't necessarily mean that those computers were down.
It might also mean that maybe you don't have enough computers inside a swarm that have those missing chunks.
Or it means that maybe your computer was not able to share enough chunks
with other nodes as well,
because all of those nodes were already replicated on other machines.
Okay, but anyways, this is how the bTorrent protocol works.
So, the tracker acts as a superpeer that basically can detect other nodes
and keeps track of other nodes that contain files.
And then we contact those trackers by extracting them from a Torrent file
that is built by other nodes.
So by having this again multi-layered architecture in a sense, it was very hard for people to blame on the companies that were maintaining the web servers.
Because the web servers, they were just maintaining the torrent files of the trackers.
They were not storing any kind of data.
So again, we know that the BitTorrent is used to transfer data illegally, especially copyrighted
data.
But because the service where you find the torrent files, it's very hard to prosecute
the web servers because they don't store the data itself.
They just store information about the tracker that actually keep track of the nodes that
actually have the data.
So it's very hard to figure out who's responsible.
But they move the responsibility now to the users.
So now if somebody is downloading that data, they're at fault, not the website.
Okay.
All right.
Let's take a quick break now for 15 minutes.
Let's come back at 7.45.
And then we'll talk about what the book calls hybrid system architecture.
So these are more complex architectures of distributed systems.
but we'll see how we can understand them
by looking at them from the lens
of either logical architectures
or the physical architectures of the system.
But they can be a combination of all of them.
Okay?
But let's take a break.
Let's come back at 7.45
and we'll continue talking about this.
Okay?
I'm going to try it.
yeah
is there supposed to be a tornado today or something?
I don't think so
I was overhearing you talking about tornadoes
oh is there a tornado warning?
I haven't got anything
usually they don't strike in the city though
I know they've hit like on the lake
a little further out
never go in the water
Yeah.
Because, if you're not enjoying it, it's so technical.
Right.
My turn is bad.
I enjoy it too.
No people in the weather.
No.
I got to see one at the same time, I don't really want to see one, you know.
Yeah, they're terrifying.
Yeah.
How was this up in the end?
there was a water spot one time like four or five years ago and that was like a tornado that hit over your water.
that doesn't happen to a lot from me.
At least as of right now.
just want it to be cold enough that it doesn't downpour and it just snows.
As long as it's not so cold, but it doesn't snow either, that'll happen.
You know, it's, we're looking at the next two to three years.
my quote says put on everything from here.
Yeah.
Might as well just sit on it.
And then it's there.
And then it's it's a place.
Right.
It was in .
Yeah.
So, it's in .
And Couteau is as far out as you want to go.
Because we were up on a, keep going that direction.
I had a question about super peers.
Who manages that?
Is like the application manage it or is it just random users that join and get randomly
assigned to be super peers or?
It depends on the application.
So what's important to understand is that, again, when somebody builds the application,
you build one application for the weak peers and one application for the super peers, and
then whoever wants to run it.
So it depends if this is part of an organization, then you have a sysadmin that just deploys
it on multiple computers, maybe geographically distribute it, and they all connect with each
other and they talk.
If it's like, again, more like an application like BitTor, and then, yeah, people who volunteer,
they run the systems.
And do they have to be persistent?
Can it be like the cord where if they leave, all of the nodes they manage get transferred to somebody else?
Correct, correct, correct.
Yeah, so a lot of the times the super peers might be run by interested parties,
but they can be designed in a way where there is no party of interest that runs them.
We'll see, we'll go all the way at the end, we'll have the blockchain.
For blockchain, there's no one single entity that manages everything.
It's everything, everyone that is involved can either act as a user of the system or a validator inside that system.
That validates all of the transactions that happen, for example, in the blockchain system.
So anyways, long story short, it just depends on the application.
But yeah, sometimes it's run by people who are just dedicated and they run those things.
Sometimes, you know, they're managed by somebody.
So context depending based on like what's available?
Correct.
correct and that's my price range well that's my question like they used to pirate everything and
they made it really cheap to access services like Netflix or something and then they made
it really expensive so pirate games coming back so people are going there not saying we're doing
piratey I'm just saying yep yep I walked out gotta have your own home server again even worse is when
they said about video games right that the video games that I got from steam they're not taking
even yours.
Yeah.
I mean, at that point I'm like, well, why
you pay for them?
If they're not mine.
Yeah.
There's money on it.
I just rented for a couple weeks.
Were they turning off servers of old games
that people still play and stuff?
Yeah, I'm like, the darkest spot east of Mississippi.
Yeah.
In the distribution you talked about vertical distribution.
Which one is better?
It depends on the situation, right?
So sometimes it may be very hard for a layer
to be split across the machine.
Like the consistency issues, it depends.
The easiest one is to do verticals.
You should worry.
Basically, each layer goes on a different machine.
But I mean the most if we start to work.
Yeah, it will be more costly.
But in AI centers, we have...
No, in AI they do...
So the same layer, for example, that does the inference is just distributed across multiple
machines and whenever they have a request, it gets forward to a machine or another.
But isn't this about the hardware?
This is about applications.
It's about how do you distribute the logical components of the reputation on different
computers.
I thought this was about the hardware.
It's not necessarily about the hardware but it can be applied to hardware as well.
For example, if you want to run a model that is really large and you want to run it across
multiple machines, that is still considered horizontal distribution.
You split your model with different machines and it is your own computation.
Of course the only difference is that you have to aggregate at some point.
That's how they do the training of these large AI models, right?
It's horizontal distribution.
But it's more specific because it's only one app.
It's the app of training.
So if you were to describe it, it has more to do with horizontal scale.
It's multiple components to accelerate the performance of the stuff in each.
How do you distribute the structure of that piece?
Well at a certain point it's like I don't want everything popping up on my computer.
I wanted to ask about, I can't turn them off.
You can ask me now yeah.
It's more like, I don't know where did I record it.
So I was trying to set up with my server that I have it most.
Apparently I did it on this because I was having too much problems.
I don't have to worry about it.
How many puppies can I add?
As many as you want.
The only problem is when you get flown, you can only add one key on the jump host.
So that's the default.
So what I would do is I would just copy that private key.
Okay so currently I was working on servers trying to do but I wasn't able to so I installed
on this but it doesn't have a lot of storage so I want to work on that.
Yeah, just copy your product.
Okay.
Currently I just push with the public.
No, no, no.
So no, no you don't push.
VS Code does, Visual Studio.
Visual Studio.
It's a clean, but you need to generate two keys, right?
public, you uploaded it at the enterprise.
So put it in the Jupyter as well.
OK.
Yeah.
So what happens, if you want to use another machine,
that machine needs to have access to the private key
to use the exact same location.
Both of the Jupyter and .
OK.
I just wanted to read the deadline.
Yeah, no I understand, yeah.
But if you copy it.
Did you optimize C++?
You should be able to, make sure you have the same permission
and the same location.
OK.
and the same slash...
Once you have that, you'll be able to do git clone and stuff.
I'll probably have to do the tailgate thing the other day.
The what?
The tailgap.
Oh, tailscale.
Tailscale.
Yeah, I mean, there'll be another way if you want to...
Yeah, if you do tailscale, I mean, this compared to that...
Sometimes, you do... most of the time.
Yeah, that works as well.
I also was confused, like, with the open-due server.
Is there any way that on the VM I can run the whole code instead of just the terminal?
It's easier for you, after Programming Assignment 1, you can put a graphical user interface on it.
So there is a command that you can use to install, so up to you.
If you want to do it that way, if it's easier, go for it.
It doesn't really matter. For Programming Assignment 1, I wanted to use the command-
But with Programming Assignment 2, you can increase the RAM in the VM, the number of
cores, you can extend the VM.
That's good to know.
It's not like it's not necessarily especially now.
I have an extra lab now.
I was just trying to install the whole SSD crash so it just went dead.
Everything went wrong with the hardware.
I got it.
I know that again when you put the graph for you, it will be slower.
It will be slower?
Because he has to go a lot of graphical computations, the command line is just text
That's why the reason why I
I'll just think if you want just connect your code editor to your machine
Just do remote development
it's just on.
Thank you.
I'm not going to be data engineering,
if it's going to be some systems thing,
or if that's going to be.
Yeah, data engineering is everywhere right now,
especially with AI and stuff.
That's all basically data engineering.
Yeah.
I'm just trying to get like a job.
Get paid, and you're going to live your life.
I don't know if you have a stable life for a little while.
Yeah, absolutely.
Maybe you'll even have some money left over savings.
We never know.
Never know.
The way I can tell I'm 80.
The cool thing about this is you're not destroying your body.
I have a buddy of mine, I used to work in healthcare for a little while.
The amount of time you lift patients and you use your lower back.
And the hours too.
Yeah, I mean the hours weren't so bad, at least for me.
But at the same time, it's just like you're destroying your back.
This is a certain point. I have a buddy who's like his pinched nerves in his like spine. I don't know what it's called
But essentially it's just in pain
That's not certain. It's hard to fix or alleviate and do. It sucks. Basically just has to rest it and then
Eventually we all sell our body one way or another under capitalism
At least with this you're learning something every day so it keeps away with the Alzheimer's.
As long as you stay like active, you're good.
That's a problem because I'm sitting down like eight hours out of a day so my posture gets really bad.
Timur's meant to walk, so if you don't want to.
I go for like a five mile walk every day.
Nice. That's good.
Just, I don't know, it makes me feel better.
It does. It absolutely does. I got a dog and I have to walk him every day.
He likes to walk a lot.
But yeah, it's so good for your mental health.
Like some days I just stop feeling it, I feel terrible.
I go walk, and I come back, I'm like, alright, I don't know why I was feeling bad.
It's so much better now.
There's definitely points where I don't get like how to fix a certain piece of code or something.
Then I go for a walk and I come back, and it's like, oh, there it is.
Yeah, absolutely. You need to give your brain time to like, process it.
Sleep on it a little bit.
I was joking, I'm doing a Systems1 class.
There's a lot of bit manipulation.
I was joking, I was dreaming in ones and zeros.
My brain was solving the bit operation, well I'm just...
That's pretty funny.
Can't escape it.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's cool.
The options are super cool.
I was talking with the professor that they should make a Sudoku book,
a bit operation for puzzles, just because it's basically like Sudoku,
but in a different way of thinking about it.
You just do pushes and , and stuff.
It's fun.
And that does not make for readable code, though.
No, I mean it's not applicable to really anything at this point.
I used to be big on, like, oh, I'll make my code look super sophisticated and very cool,
and then I'd come back to it a week later like, oh, what the fuck was that doing?
What did you do again?
So I did a couple things.
One was a software tester for an IOT company.
Great.
And then the other one was basically scripting robots to like promotions and stuff.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
The company built sort of machines to automate manufacturing processes.
Smart manufacturing?
Smaller stuff more like putting lots of metal into lates or sorting things or
palletizing and stuff.
At Amazon, for anything?
Yeah, kinda like where we go in the warehouse.
Most of the systems that pick things,
put them on a conveyor belt,
and then they brought them to wherever they need to go,
so they can package it through something.
I've been in the Amazon warehouse for a month.
That's how long it lasted for hours like I came.
This isn't gonna be for me.
Slave drivers.
I mean, you barely have enough time to go to the break room.
And then at the break room, you have like a T or something.
And then you go back to work and it's like, it's a longer than average shift.
And they measure everything.
So if you slow down a little bit, like, yeah, it's like that sweet spot between,
like, you can't zone out and you can't listen to music.
So you have to be aware of everything.
So you can't really focus.
But if you focus too much on what you're doing at the same time,
you're not achieving the, so I just don't recommend Amazon warehouse.
Right. Yeah, I feel like the way they make their metrics don't really take humans into account.
No.
It really sucks.
Because like, delivery drivers, they don't even have time to go use the bathroom.
That's what they're talking about in New York at the moment.
But, yeah.
I mean, they have great benefits.
Like, they'll pay for like, community college and all that stuff.
Yeah, yeah.
They give you like, healthcare and everything.
But, like, I ended up working at, like, a restaurant, like a wine cook kind of thing instead for a little while.
Just because I was, like, I'm not going to.
This was in between.
Yeah, and you'll still have to have time to live your life.
Well, I mean, I feel like there are some jobs where you can be a human being,
and there are some jobs where it's, like, I just don't remember what I did.
I was just there.
That's not good.
No, it's not good.
I'm actually criticised warehouse words, that's a good word.
Yeah, unfortunately, like you said, the metrics that people use take humans into
Like, I grew up in Seattle, so Amazon is a big part of like where people talk about
because they own 75% of the physical city.
So there's just a ton of Amazon workers.
And they all talk about how 10% has to be fired every single year.
So I was like, I moved to Seattle.
It's going to be great.
And then after a year, they get fired.
And I just moved across the country.
And now I'm part of the layoffs.
And then you have all the other big tech companies.
So basically, you're fighting other people who come from the big tech.
I don't think it's a very sustainable way to live.
but...
I traveled to Seattle.
It's a beautiful section.
It's, yeah, but I read about the history.
I was curious.
The history?
The history, you know, how the city developed and yeah, I did read about, again, big tech
companies and stuff.
They changed even, yeah, they changed the policies of the city.
They influenced, they lobbied a lot.
There's anyways, a lot of things that I think people who have been living there for a long
time, they're unsatisfied.
Well, I mean, a big criticism that locals have is there's no state income tax, which is great in some senses because you're going to keep more of your money, but it's bad in the sense that you don't have taxes for social issues.
So it's just like tech companies keep all the money and they don't give anything back to the community that's helping them.
Unless they benefit from it.
Yeah.
I don't want to get too far into politics.
let's go back to distributed systems
then and I know we're going to talk about cloud computing
and I'm going to use Amazon as an example
but anyways
let's try to understand it maybe for
what it is in terms of
logical achievement and then
of course when it comes to
deploying these technologies, building applications
just don't forget one thing
in the end these are all built for humans
so you have to have at least
a little bit of a human centric
overview of it because you can build
these things they're not you know impossible to build you know but the
question is do they actually serve anyone in a good way that's a different story
this would be for you to decide this is where again I feel like AIs cannot
replace human judgment artists. All right but going back to you know other kinds
of let's say architectures so let's start talking about cloud computing
systems because they are in a category of their own and we can try to
to understand why. And they are in a category of their own because cloud computing systems,
they're a little bit different than data centers or computer clusters or supercomputers.
So cloud computing systems, they follow a specific philosophy which is called utility
computing philosophy. So through utility computing, what people try to achieve is they try to
achieve a system that provides computational resources to people that need them in a continuous
ways, similar to electricity
and water, right? So
electricity,
right, and water is, you know, if you need to
use a certain amount of electricity or
water, you turn on the tap, you plug in your device,
you turn on the device, right, and then once
you're done using it, you turn it off, and you pay how
much you use, right? You paid how much kilowatts
did you use per hour, and then you
pay, you know, for how much quantity of water
you used, you know, gallons or whatever they used to
measure.
So people wanted to build computer
systems that acted in a similar way, that provided computing resources to people as
much as they needed, and they would pay OA for that amount.
And then when they don't need it anymore, they can shut off those computing resources
and don't have to pay for that.
Why did we need to do this?
Well, let's go back in time a little bit before cloud computing systems.
Let's say that you are a small startup and you had this cool idea that you wanted to
implement.
But in order to be able to test their application, maybe it was a larger scale application, maybe
It was a distributed application, which means that you needed some sort of computing infrastructure to test it on.
You cannot just put this application in a Play Store, and then hopefully people will use it, and hopefully it will be okay.
You need to test it in a controlled environment.
So this infrastructure still is very expensive to build.
You have to buy the servers.
You have to buy the network equipment.
You have to pay system administrators to set it up, network administrators to network everything, to manage everything.
do I secure everything?
Right?
So that's actually a lot of resources that, you know,
small companies or startups,
they might necessarily have to be able to bootstrap their project.
Now, at the same time, right,
the Amazon Web Store started expanding, right?
So they started selling not just only books,
but they started selling, you know,
anything that can be sold legally on the internet.
Right?
So one thing that they observed, right,
and this is tied, again, to the philosophy of, you know,
their CEO, so Jeff Bezos at the time, you know,
He was a very client-centric, let's say, businessman.
He always wanted to focus to satisfy the client.
So if somebody wants to come to Amazon and buy something, I want to be able for them to buy that thing.
I don't want to deny them.
I don't want them to send the request and then get a timeout or whatever.
I want everyone to be served.
So to be able to do this, they had to buy enough computing infrastructure to be able to serve all of the requests that were coming in.
Now, one pattern that they observed is that during certain times throughout the year,
especially around holidays, Black Friday, Cyber Monday, there was a spike in requests.
A lot of people were buying a lot of things.
It was stressing their infrastructure.
Basically, in order to be able to satisfy an increasing number of requests, buy more hardware,
which they did.
According to Jeff Bezos, let's build it.
We want everyone to be able to buy stuff, especially during the holidays.
But then the question was, what do we do with those computers during regular time where the requests go low?
You know, they can decrease by orders of magnitude, right?
So what do we do with those computers?
Because, you know, if you keep them on, I mean, they waste energy.
If you turn them off, they still depreciate, right?
You still need to do maintenance over them.
They still break over time.
For certain components, for example, for SSDs, you have to connect them to electricity.
Otherwise, your data gets lost or the internal systems get corrupted over time.
So they have to be used.
So then that's where they thought about, okay, what if we can maybe share these computers with people that need it?
And they can rent these computers out for a shorter period of time.
So this started intersecting with this notion of utility computing.
And in the end, what allowed Amazon to build their Amazon AWS, you know, cloud services was actually also a very important piece of technology called virtualization.
So virtualization, right, is this technology that allows you to actually abstract and carve out parts of a computer by creating virtual components of a real computer, right?
So, if we look here, the first layer of a cloud system is always going to be the hardware system.
What else are doing right now?
Anyways, the first layer is the hardware, right?
So, this is defined by the computers that are part of the data center or data centers that make up a cloud system.
And the computers, they provide some basic resources.
They provide CPU.
They provide memory, disk, network.
These are the very simple resources.
Now, for somebody who has a startup and they want to build an application,
they need these kinds of resources in order to test out their applications.
Now, one way is that you can rent out a physical computer if you want,
but a lot of the time people don't need a very large computer.
Maybe they need something smaller.
Maybe they just need something that just emulates an Android phone or a 100 iOS phones.
They can run it in separate virtual machines, let's say.
So this is where virtualization allowed them to then build this, you know, system that, you know, could give people, you know, a part of a computer, a small part of a computer with, you know, they can specify how many cores, how much RAM, how much storage, what kind of network, you know, capabilities do you want on those machines, right?
And they can provide these as a resource, as a continuous resource.
So if somebody wants to use it for a short amount of time to run an experiment, let's say for three days, they can do that, right?
And then they can shut off these VMs, and they only have to pay for the amount of time that they use those machines.
Now, of course, when it comes to cloud computing systems versus self-hosted architecture, right, there's always the question, you know, which one is better, which one is cheaper?
The question usually gets answered once you do an analysis to see over how long of a period of time you're going to use the system.
If you just need, for example, and you have another idea and you need an AI model and you want to train an AI model, but you need a powerful workstation to do that, you can buy the workstation, which will be very expensive.
or you can rent if your AMR only takes, you know, let's say a day to run in the cloud,
you probably just rent the machine in the cloud, right?
It would be way cheaper than buying the actual infrastructure just to train for one day.
Now, if you know your application will need to run this training for a very long period of time, right,
it might make more sense to buy your own infrastructure and then it will be cheaper.
But it depends.
So you need to make this, in a sense, analysis to see for a certain application in business, you know,
does it make more sense to use resources from the cloud or does it make more sense to buy your own infrastructure?
Unfortunately, I think right now the trends, especially with, you know, the increasing price in memory,
I think it makes it very easy for the cloud vendors to actually buy a lot of the RAM,
buy a lot of the computing systems, and then make it so that, you know, for regular users to buy a server,
it's going to become more expensive than to actually rent it in the cloud,
which is kind of unfortunate because if you have access to the physical system,
especially from a learning perspective, you end up learning more than just using something in the cloud.
Anyways, so using this technology, it allowed them to build the first layer
that resides in cloud computing systems,
which is the infrastructure layer.
So again, cloud computing systems,
they're organized as layers, right?
We can use the layering technique
to actually understand how they're organizing structure.
So the infrastructure layer provides
what they call in cloud computing systems,
infrastructure as a service.
So this means that they allow you
to create virtual machines with virtual processors,
virtual memory, virtual disk, virtual network.
You can also create network storage devices that can be attached to your virtual machines if you want to.
You can create, of course, you can use objects for a system, so on and so forth.
So this is the kind of resources that you get whenever you access a cloud, either a public cloud or a private cloud.
It allows you to create virtual machines that reside on those computers.
Now, of course, the price of those virtual machines, they change according to the supply and demand, right?
So Amazon has a certain supply of servers, right?
And depending on how many people are coming and buying, they can increase or decrease the prices.
You know, it might be worth studying to see what happens with those prices when they have those spikes, you know, during Black Friday, during, you know, Cyber Monday, when people buy a lot of stuff, right?
It would be interesting to see, you know, how the prices change for the games.
But generally speaking, right, again, they can change depending on how many users they have.
All right, so this is the first layer, which provides, again, basically virtual machines.
And we know that virtual machines are software representation of hardware.
So this means that you can run operating systems on them, you can install compilers.
So if anyone works on a project, they can go use that resource, set up their system whichever way they want.
They get root permission on the machine.
They can install packages, set it up, whichever way they want.
Now, I just want to mention as well that most public clouds out there, including Amazon AWS, Google Cloud Platform, Microsoft Azure,
they usually give you virtual machines as resources.
But there exist other clouds that can also give you access to bare metal machines.
And actually, Chameleon Cloud, which we will be using in this class, actually, it's a bare metal cloud that provides you access to a physical machine.
and they use a different mechanism to make sure that people don't abuse the systems and that they
use the resources they might fully and we'll see you once we introduce comedian cloud and we'll
see how that works now one thing that people have observed when people started building these clouds
and using these virtual machines that were running in the clouds is sometimes for you know a software
developer is they didn't necessarily care about what operating system was running on that vm which
version of the compiler.
They didn't really care about those details.
What did matter for them is that, hey, I'm building a web application.
I just need a database and a web server.
That's all that I need.
I don't need to know
what operating system is, the database
running on, when it was last updated,
I don't really care about it.
So this now introduces us to another layer
that exists inside CloudContinue Systems,
which is the platform layer.
Or the layer that provides
platform as a service services.
So in this layer, people who are designing cloud systems, they realize that people sometimes maybe just need access to a database that sits in an isolated environment. Maybe sometimes they need access to a web server. Maybe sometimes they need access to some sort of big data computational framework like Hadoop or Spark.
That's all that they needed.
They didn't really need an actual VM where they had to set up a network,
the users, they didn't really care about it.
They just wanted a place where they were able to run applications and test applications.
So they started providing different kinds of platform-as-a-service services,
such as Database as a Service, Hadoop as a Service, Web Server as a Service.
Now you can just create these services instead of spawning VMs.
What's interesting is that, of course, the platform layer makes use of the layer below.
So all of these platforms are actually created on top of virtual machines
that are set up in the infrastructure layer.
And the infrastructure layer makes use of the hardware underneath it.
They're all deployed on the physical machines.
And then lastly, they also realize that people maybe sometimes
they just need access to certain applications,
like word processing applications or spreadsheets.
Maybe they just want to watch, you know, videos on YouTube or on Netflix.
So they also built another layer that sits on top of the platforms layer,
which is the application layer.
And this is the layer that provides software as a service, let's say services.
So it allows you to basically run different kind of apps.
Now, if I were to ask you, you know,
if you've had a chance to use any of these AI tools like chat GPT,
you know, in which layer would you say that, you know,
systems like chat GPT fall?
because in the application there are platforms, infrastructure, and hardware there.
It depends on the implementation, but, you know, if you were to throw a guess, you know, where might it be?
So application, most of the times, especially if you just use the chat,
I know that they also created these, you know, agent development stuff,
so that could be, you know, in the platform area,
because now it's spawning other agents, doing other computation, right?
It's using no resources, you can create containers where you can test the application, right?
So depending on how you use these AI tools, if you just use the prompt, you know, it's in the application side.
But if you use these advanced, you know, agentic tools, you can go in the platform area as well.
All right.
But again, the most important aspect is that, again, cloud computing systems, even though they're very complex,
they might use various kinds of layers.
Or right here, you might have, for example, the infrastructure layer might be implemented,
maybe using a peer-to-peer system,
maybe using a publisher-subscriber, who knows.
But you can understand that it's the higher-level layers
by using the layer in, let's say, a approach.
All right, and everything that I mentioned here,
you'll be able to find them, of course, in the slides.
I'm going to keep on moving forward.
I don't think I've covered really a lot
when we talked about introduction.
There was a discussion about edge computing systems.
So just to understand, so once cloud computing systems became, you know, more and more popular,
people realized that they can offset computation from edge devices.
Edge devices could mean, you know, sensors, you know, smart TVs, smart, I don't know, refrigerators.
It also means smartphones as well.
They can move the heavy computation from the device itself to the cloud.
So, right, for example, if you wanted to have translating capabilities on your phone,
instead of, you know, putting, you know,
a particle processor on your phone and more RAM
and more computation capabilities,
which made the phone very expensive,
you could offload actually the computation
in the cloud and do it there.
So that's how Google Translate works
or Google Lens, right?
Whenever you use Translate,
it actually gets sent somewhere in the cloud
and this is a translation for you.
You can still download, I think, models locally
because now they use AI.
They can compress the models,
but they're more powerful when you use them in the cloud.
And then for Google Lens, you have to use cloud
because there's image processing that has to be done to convert, for example,
a text from one language to the other that you can see on your phone.
So this is typically done in the cloud.
But the main problem is if you now have all of these edge devices,
if they all send their computation more and more to the cloud,
you're going to reach certain limitations.
The limitations have to do with network bandwidth.
There's so much network that you have until you reach the limits
of how much you can send over the network.
So then people started exploring with a different kind of system,
especially for, let's say, edge devices that collaborate together.
Let's say, you know, edge devices that might reside in a factory,
you know, sensors and actuators in a factory of smart cities
or even inside a normal organization.
So people started building edge computing systems.
So these are, again, computer clusters that sit in between the edge devices
and the cloud computing systems.
And they can serve various purposes.
They can implement various kinds of services.
In reality, when DePaul does that, so for example, DePaul makes use of the cloud systems provided by Microsoft to manage email and accounts.
But for example, when they record the classrooms and everything, these are all stored on a local server.
And in order to have very good latency, they probably have an edge computer system in the Loop campus and in another edge computer system in the Lingampar campus.
And they transfer data locally from the classrooms to their servers and they process them, after which they upload them to the cloud.
That's why it takes a little bit of time for the recording to be available on B2L.
It's not available immediately after we finish the lecture.
It usually takes about two hours to be uploaded.
So again, these are examples on how people can set up these edge, let's say, computer systems.
Sometimes they call them edge networks that connects to different kinds of networks.
What's very important to know, and of course there are more details over here,
What's very important to know is that understanding how to build and how to manage these edge, let's say, systems, but also edge computing systems, it's still an open problem.
There's still a lot of companies that are working on building frameworks and platforms for automatically managing edge devices and edge computing systems.
There's still a lot of work that is done in the area of resource allocation, service placement, edge selection.
so if you are at some point interested
and you want to really decide
hey I want to become a distributed systems engineer
I would search for companies that are
working in this area and I would
do more reading in this area to learn
what people are doing to see
if you can contribute to their system
and help them build a framework that can manage
all of these devices. Unfortunately
with cloud computing systems they're easier
to manage because you have a uniform
infrastructure that you can build, you know what
goes on there, it's controlled by one organization
for edge devices, it's harder, and for edge computing systems, it's harder as well,
because they can change from one application to the other.
They might use different services, right?
So it might become a little bit harder to manage and to orchestrate
than cloud computing systems.
So there's still a lot of work that people are doing here,
and there's still a lot of open-ended questions on how do we do things,
especially with AI, how do we do things securely as well?
All right.
and now the last kind of example of a more complex architecture
let's also take a look at blockchains as well
because these are also very interesting
I know before AI became a thing
and before content became a thing
I think blockchain was the hype
everyone was talking about it
we did blockchain and everything
and like cryptocurrencies are the future
and you know it's all great
but I think it's important for us to just understand them
at least in terms of computer architecture
what made them different than other computer systems.
So what blockchain systems try to solve is the problem of how do we manage,
let's say, a connection of, let's say, transactions in a system.
Transaction means I'm doing certain kinds of operations in the system.
How do we keep a sequence of those transactions consistent across multiple computers
where we cannot trust the computers?
and there's no one central entity that we can trust.
Okay, so in order to do this,
it means that we had to design a system.
It's basically a peer-to-peer system.
It's a system where everyone can act
with both its clients and servers.
And the actual roles that we have there in the system
is we have participants in the systems
and then systems that maintain the blockchain network.
And what the participants can do
is they can perform transactions inside the system.
Whenever a participant performs a transaction,
it broadcasts a transaction to all of the possible nodes
that are connected to the system.
So whatever you do, for example,
a Bitcoin transaction is a broadcast.
It happens that, hey, I'm doing this transaction right now.
And multiple compute nodes can capture that transaction.
Now, of course, there's also the notion of validate R-NOS.
So these are nodes that collect all of the transactions
and they try to put them in a list of transactions
or a chain of transactions.
Well, they don't put it in a chain.
They put, actually, the transactions inside one block.
And then what they try to do is they try to append the block
to an existing chain of blocks of transactions.
But this needs to be consistent.
In order to be consistent, it means that the other nodes have to trust
that the operation was done correctly.
The way that they do this is by collecting all of the blocks,
validating the transactions, and then solving a very complex puzzle
in order to decide which of the nodes is allowed to append to the blockchain.
Because the computational puzzle is very hard,
only one of the machines can do it.
And because it costs a lot of resources to do it,
we then believe the machines.
And then we can easily validate the results of that puzzle.
So let's go over the system and look at a little bit of the properties
and let's see what it would take to create the system
and to move from, let's say, a centralized solution to a distributive solution
and to a decentralized solution.
So again, some important properties.
The blocks organized in the blockchain are organized in an unforgeable append-only chain.
So once you append the block to the chain and expand the chain,
the chain cannot be modified anymore.
So it's append-only.
So it keeps, again, track of the history of all of the transactions.
So since the blockchain cannot be modified anymore, so it's immutable,
You can massively replicate the blockchain.
So anyone can go over the blockchain and validate all of the transactions.
That's how they make sure that, you know, nobody lies whenever they do transactions with Bitcoins.
Or if they lie, they can be detected.
And then the transaction can be cancelled.
Right.
But the problem is, you know, how do you append a block to a blockchain?
So this can be implemented, of course, using a centralized solution.
That would be the easiest way.
Right.
A centralized solution means you have a central computer.
that it's responsible with attaching the blocks to the blockchain.
So if anyone wants to do transactions,
they add them to the block and then send the block to the centralized entity.
The centralized entity can validate the transaction,
make sure that everything consists,
and make sure that nobody modified the blockchain.
Everything is good.
You move both.
But again, the problem is this is not a decentralized solution.
And the question is if somebody compromises the centralized system,
right we cannot trust them as we cannot trust the bank when they developed
critical practices now we can also implement a distributed solution so
distributed solutions we select a subset of the nodes to be responsible with
deciding right if certain you know blockchain is correct or not and then
to then decide if we want to
append a block to the blockchain.
So these systems, they can, you know, build their
own consensus there or algorithms
to determine which one is correct or which
one is true. The only problem
with this is that the more nodes
you add, the more communication
we have to do between them,
then it becomes
from a scalability point of view, very hard to achieve.
Now, if you have a small number of nodes, this still becomes dangerous because they
can get compromised and you cannot trust the system, right?
So you want to have a larger number.
So then the solution was to build a decent solution.
Again, it's called a permissionless solution where the nodes can play either the role of
participants or validators or both at the same time.
Now, the participants, what they do is they collectively engage in a distributed leader election.
So basically, what they try to do is whenever they have a block that is ready to be appended to the blockchain,
you will allow only one of the compute nodes to actually append that block to the blockchain.
And in order to choose that leader, they use some sort of election system that needs to be fair, robust, secure, which is far from, let's say, trivial.
Now, we will talk more about how they implement this leader election a little bit later when we talk about, I think, coordination in distributed systems.
When we look at the actual algorithm and how they use, let's say, hash functions to determine who is the winner of this leader election.
But again, this allows now only one of the systems
to add data to the blockchain.
Whenever that, let's say, a participant
wins the leader election, it can be validated
that it was the one that won the election
and then they can append the data.
And the algorithm is designed in a way
where somebody who appended, let's say,
information to the data will have a very hard time
of pinning information again very soon.
So other systems, you know, will be, let's say,
probabilistically selected randomly out of the entire system in order to
append data and update the blockchain. The blockchain again is then massively
distributed across all of the other nodes. Since the blockchain itself is
immutable, it means that everyone can restart a leader election whenever they
want to add transactions to the network. So whenever you've heard of the notion of
mining bitcoin the processes that were mining bitcoin were actually the processes that were
maintaining the network i know how you were asking you know earlier you know who runs the super peers
in a super peer network the validators they kind of act as a super peer so the participants they
can you know do transactions they have the wallets that they exchange money and everything right but
they have to do it to these validator nodes so the validator nodes act as super peers and these are
one in this case in the case of bitcoin they are run by volunteers so people who want to run the
network this could be organizations this could be various kinds of people right they want this and
the way this uh the bitcoin network was designed was that you know whoever volunteer their systems
to actually maintain the network will also get paid a certain amount from the network
okay all right very good so that's all that i wanted to cover when it comes to
to architectures and distributed systems,
what I'm going to do is, I think I'm going to start
talking about processes, and next week,
after programming assignment two,
we'll talk about programming assignment three.
In programming assignment three,
you'll need to implement the same 5-3-volt engine
as in programming assignment two.
But you will need to use multi-threading
to actually increase the performance
of the indexing process.
You will see that I don't want to spoil this company,
what happens when we do the performance evaluation,
but you will see that the indexing part of the program
actually takes the most amount of time.
Once you do the index, search happens relatively fast.
So the question is about how do we build this index fast?
And to do that, we use multi-trade.
So let me go ahead and download the slides for the next chapter.
And we can start talking about it a little bit, and then we'll go into more details next time.
I'm just going to start the conversation for now, since we still have a little bit of time left.
All right.
So the third chapter in the book is called Processes.
and the way that the book likes to define what a component of a distributed system is,
because we talk about the architectures and we have components.
But we didn't really say what those components are.
We didn't really describe them.
So the book likes to describe them as processes.
I know that you've also encountered probably the notion of processes in Systems 1 or Systems 2,
where you talked a little bit about the operating system.
Right. Now, if I were to ask, you know, to define it using, you know, natural language, you know, whichever way you want to explain, you know, what is a process in a computer?
Process is a process.
I like it. The cyclic definitions, you know.
I have a set of instructions that are running.
A set of instructions that are running, that's the most important part.
So actually, I will tie it the definition of a program, right?
So you learn first what a program is.
A program, right, it's basically a set of instructions, right,
that you would like that CPU to execute.
Now, a program in execution, when it's running on the CPU,
it's called a process.
Okay?
All right.
So that's what a process is.
Now, of course, a process can mean various things,
inside of the distributive system, but we will start actually with this definition first.
So that's what we will discuss next time as well.
Now I do want to mention something.
So when a process runs on a computer, right?
A process can be in a specific state.
Do you remember what are the states of a process?
It can be idle.
So idle means that it's not doing anything useful, right?
So it's just sitting there.
But what other states?
Running.
So this is, again, when the process is actually running on the process.
So what other states?
Sleeping or waiting.
Sleeping or waiting, right?
So when the process is waiting for data from the disk, it goes into a sleeping queue, right?
And then a sleeping queue.
And then it can also be waiting when the process, right, gets scheduled from the CPU out so that
another process comes in.
Okay?
All right.
Very good.
So using these notions, right, we can see that processes can have a certain state.
Now, when I studied distributive systems many years ago, I had a professor that used to say,
and he was very adamant about, you know, making sure that we understand that a distributive system does not have a state.
That you cannot really define, let's say, from pure mathematical point of view, or logical point of view,
a distributed system cannot have a state. Why? Because
a distributed system is made out of many computers, a collection
of computers. You can have various processes running on these computers
that are running the distributed system itself. Each process
has its own state. And you cannot take
a snapshot at one moment of time and say that, oh, the distributed system
state is actually the collection of all of the states of all of the processes.
The number of processes can change in a distributed system.
You know, it's very hard to create some sort of unique clock to determine, you know,
oh, this is the snapshot that I'm going to take, you know, across all of the computers
on all of the data centers in the world, and that will be the state that describes the system.
This has to do, again, with the limitations imposed by the laws of physics, right?
So we know if we, you know, try to integrate into this discussion,
the general theory of relativity, right, where again the clocks of different systems will
act differently or will increment differently according to how they move in accordance to
each other, right.
So the data centers, they spin around, right, and they might exhibit different clocks.
And we'll see this is a general problem when it comes to computers and how do you synchronize
these clocks.
So it's very hard to determine to create a general state of the distributed system.
You have states per processes but not inside the distributing system.
All right.
With the parentheses closed, I think the last thing that I want to do today without jumping too much into detail.
So what we'll do is next time we'll talk about processes, we'll talk about threads, and we'll see what the difference between threads and processes are.
Because I mentioned that you have to use multi-threading techniques.
We'll also try to put threads in the context of the architectures of the processors.
So I'm going to draw more stuff on the whiteboard, actually.
And then we'll also put it back into the context of what you learn in computer systems, too,
which is we'll put it back into the context of what is a processor
and how processes run on a processor,
what is the role of virtual memory, right, and why do we need it,
and how does it work in the context of threads, right,
what happens with that virtual memory when we have multiple threads,
and why do we need multiple threads.
All right, very good.
But for now, the only other thing that I want to mention is just a few pieces of terminology that I want to define.
And I think after that, we can slowly wrap up the class.
So, first things first, let's try to understand a little bit the history of how process orders evolved over time, and why do we have this notion of processes that are running on the processor.
And then I know there is a notion called, I'll put it over here.
So there's a notion called multiprocessing.
So multiprocessing, right, which you might have heard before.
But if you've heard it before, can you explain to me what does multiprocessing mean?
Yes, we do.
Yes.
A lot of processes running at once?
Exactly.
So a lot of processes kind of running at once.
All right, so, when people started building computers, at the beginning, computers weren't
actually very fast.
They were fast at doing a sequence of computations, but they weren't really as fast as they are
today.
But way faster than humans doing those computations on a piece of paper and more precise, especially
when they figured out how to do data representation.
Now, as the computer technology evolved,
it got to a point where the computers were so fast
that a lot of times the computers were just idling
because the humans weren't fast enough
at inserting the programs in the computers to execute.
There used to be a lot of physical involvement
whenever they loaded a program.
So then they started looking at,
okay, how can we design a system
where the people can work on the system
at the same time, write the programs, right,
and then have the system execute the programs
one after the other.
So this gave birth to some early systems
called batch processing systems.
This is where that notion of a batch script
in Windows comes from, actually.
So batch processing.
Now batch processing systems use the notion of jobs
So they didn't have the notion of processing
So each program would run as a job
And people started building a very basic operating system
Called the batch processing system
That allowed users to actually load programs
While other programs were running
Now the only difference is that the batch processing system
only allowed one program to execute at a time.
So this meant that if the program required user input,
the whole system would block until the user came
and, you know, inputted the data, right?
So this was not a very interactive system.
And it only ran one job, one process, let's say, at a time.
Now, sometimes, right, people started inserting errors
in their programs, right?
The programs weren't perfect.
So sometimes, you know, the program would crash.
which means that the entire system will crash.
So we needed to have some sort of mechanism that allowed us to run multiple processes,
multiple jobs in a safe way.
And now we see, finally, the emergence of an operating system.
So an operating system not only allows you to run jobs,
but also allows you to run these jobs in a safe way,
where if one job fails, the entire system still runs.
So it has good fault tolerance from a programming perspective, let's say.
And at the same time, the computers became so fast that if we were to execute these programs one at a time, it wouldn't be very efficient, especially if the programs required input or especially if the programs required to access data from slower devices.
As computers became faster, we started creating, again, this memory hierarchy as well.
So at the beginning, the processors, they were running as fast as the memory where you store the data, either volatile or persist.
But as technology became more advanced, it allows us to create faster processors, but with smaller amounts of registers or local memory,
which then we started creating this hierarchy of different memories to allow for greater capacity,
but at the cost of having to bring that data throughout that memory hierarchy back to the processor.
So this meant that now there were certain processes or certain jobs that were designed in a way where they were waiting for data to come from this.
Right?
And it would be very inefficient if those processes just stayed on the processor while they were waiting for data to come.
It might be more efficient to allow another process to run on the processor while the process is waiting for data.
So step by step, we started going into the area of preemptive scheduling.
So again, this problem of what process runs on the processor is called the scheduling problem.
And preemptive scheduling means that, and there are two ways to do scheduling.
There's cooperative scheduling and preemptive scheduling.
Cooperative means that the processes themselves, for example, when they detect that I have to wait for some data,
will go to sleep by themselves and will allow another process to run.
preemptively means that the operating system
will actually interrupt the processes
and will only allow them to run
for a very small amount of time,
typically measured in microseconds,
depends on nanoseconds as well,
hundreds of nanoseconds,
depends on how fast the processor is.
So modern-day operating systems
are designing a way
where they allow the processes
to run for a very small amount of time.
I'm talking about single,
four processors here,
like one process at a time,
for a very small amount,
and then it takes that process out of the processor
and it brings another process on the processor
and it makes this transition so fast
that even on a single processor computer,
for us it appears as if the system is executing processes
at the same time.
But they're not really at the same time.
Only one process at a time gets executed,
but very small parts and this quick exchange of processes
happens so fast that we don't see those changes.
We know that a monitor, for example,
refresh rate for a monitor is about 60 Hz.
Because that's what the human eye can
detect in terms of changes. Now I know you're playing video games,
maybe 120 Hz, 144, 200. Maybe if your eye
is really that trained and the latency allows you to be a better
player, then it makes sense. But for the rest of us,
60 Hz is enough. So the computers, they can do way more
computation than 60 Hz. If you remember,
Right.
A processor can execute the length of the structures per second.
So it works at 4 GHz, let's say, speed or 3 GHz speed.
So it can do way more mini-computation, which means it can schedule way more mini-processes
very fast on the processor.
And that way, it gives us the impression that multiple things are happening in the system.
So this whole idea of running these processes and interchanging them on the processor and
giving them a small amount of time to run, is called multiprocessing, like you said.
I want to be able to run multiple processes.
It gives the impression that they're running simultaneously,
but they're actually not running simultaneously.
So only one process at a time exists.
All right.
Now, we see this is very different from multithreading,
which refers to something else.
It refers to how do we organize one single application to multiple components.
So one of the problems that people started facing once they started building more advanced applications
is they noticed that one application might do multiple things at the same time.
Let's take the example of a word processor application, like Microsoft Word in the early days.
At the beginning, the word processor was simple.
It was kind of like Notepad.
You just open up, and you write, and read data, and that's it.
It doesn't do anything fancy.
But later on, people wanted to have more capabilities.
They wanted to be able to do spell checking, for example.
Right now, the way spell checking was implemented back in the day,
in the early days of Microsoft Word, is you had to press a button,
which will then tell your application,
hey, scan the entire document, identify all of the words that are incorrect,
put that red underscore under it, or line under it,
but you weren't able to modify the document while that process was running.
right so your entire application was now stuck
and you had to wait until it was done before
it read more input
maybe you wanted to
yes
did they use like an array of all of the possible words
and then compare it to the
yeah so
you can store the English
dictionary I think it's a couple of
hundreds of megabytes in size
so you can just store it on the computer
and yeah you basically compare all of the words
to the English dictionary
which is stored in a hash map
So you can easily do computation.
That's the easiest way to use it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Anyways, it's a good way to think about it,
which data structures were used.
So anyway, so again,
you have to do, again, the spellchecking process.
Maybe later on, you wanted to do automatic backup.
Maybe you want to do automatic spellchecking.
But then how do you write inside one single process,
how do you make sure the user can still type in stuff
while those other functions of your program
happen at the same time. Now, these functions can be implemented
since we have this notion of multi-processing. A processor can execute
multiple processes simultaneously. What we can do is maybe
instead of creating only one process for the Microsoft Word application
we create three processes. One process is responsible for writing data
one process is responsible for doing the spell checking and one
process is responsible for doing the automatic backup.
But the problem is, because operating systems were designed to run processes in a way where
they're isolated from each other, they now had to break that isolation.
Because the process that was being backed up had to have access to the data, but the
process that was reading the input from the user, the spell checking also had to have
access to the data, and this became very problematic to do it by using the processes.
So then people needed a different mechanism
that made it a little bit easier
to implement multiple functionalities
inside one application
without having to use different processes.
Okay?
All right.
I think what I'll do is
let's take a break here
because there's a lot more to discuss
and I want to draw some diagrams,
I think it may be better to draw them in one go
than to have them, you know,
a little bit here and then a little bit next week.
Maybe better to have them in a contiguous story.
So let's stop here.
If you have more questions, I'd be happy to take them.
Again, keep in mind, quiz number three is due by Monday.
So if you want to attend the quiz now, you can do that.
But I don't feel obligated to do it, okay?
But let's end the lecture here,
and then we'll come back and we'll talk more about
processors, processes, thread,
network to see what the advantages are, limitations and drawings and stuff.
Thank you.
I just use the one that generated yep use that multiple times well ideally you don't want to do
that it's a very bad thing to do from a security point of view yeah but to just do the assignment
make your life easier go ahead again as long as you trust your computers it's fine okay one thing
that you could do is if you want you can replace that key it has a pass I don't worry somebody
steals your key somehow passphrase they cannot use that in the yes so passphrase means when you
do git clone it asks you for a password or a passphrase key no I put the screenshot in the
private key all you don't want to put that so anyways it's okay for now good lesson I'm gonna
I'm going to hack into your system, no I'm not, okay, but never share the privacy.
I don't remember if I did or not.
Ah, okay, maybe it's just a puppy.
Hopefully, it's in the park.
But never share the privacy.
I can generate another one.
Sure, it might be better.
Just generate everything because we don't know what if somebody breaks into DePaul's,
you know, D2L system and steals the home of asylum.
That's why I put them.
Like, it was not...
They want to steal that because they want to train AIs with it, so.
I was like, it's not that complicated, so I just put a...
It's okay.
Yeah, it was part of the assignment.
It's fine.
For this assignment, it's okay.
I mean, I have some systems as well, so you cannot really do damage inside the systems,
even if somebody steals the key, you know.
I don't even remember if I put it on.
If you put it, go ahead and change it.
It'll be good practice there.
Change your key.
I'm probably going to change it.
Might be better.
Maybe.
If I don't necessarily need like a full like half hour for like an office hour, can I just email you a question or would that be?
Well yeah just email me a question and answer it.
I had a question about when you brought up virtual machines.
Talking about emulation.
You also talked about translation layers.
Yes.
What is the difference between emulation and translation layers?
That's very good.
very good question we'll actually talk about dedicated section in the processes
chapter so what visualization actually refers to it's such a general term that
can be many things and it refers to the principle of mimicking interface so
that's the main principle behind translation and emulation you're trying
to mimic an interface now at what level you're mimicking the interfaces that's
where the difference comes. An emulator tries to mimic the interface but
also the state as well. So you can have an emulator from an old NES
game but you don't emulate only the interface which is the
assembly instructions you also have to mimic the state of the
processor that was running on an NES computer. So that's what emulation is,
you're mimicking the interface plus the state. If you just do translation
you don't usually care about the states.
You're just translating one operation to another operation.
Most virtualization does a type,
actually is virtualization
where there's no translation happening at all.
So for example, when you run a virtual machine,
an x86 virtual machine on top of an x86 host computer,
there's no translation happening there.
There's only a few instructions
that get intercepted by the hypervisor
or the input-output operations,
the system calls,
then get forwarded to the hypervisor
which then get forwarded to the operating system.
But we'll talk about it as well
because there's different kinds of virtual machines.
Yeah, makes sense.
Yeah, yeah.
So we'll go over them,
but that's how you can think about it.
The main principle in virtualization
is again, you're mimicking interfaces.
my first exposure to it was using Wine on Linux
yes
and the whole point of Wine was
its abbreviation was Wine is not an emulator
yes correct correct
so it didn't try to emulate the state of the Windows kernel
because we don't know right
exactly
so it just tried to translate it
sometimes it works
sometimes it doesn't
makes sense
yeah I did really know
I think the one I generated was... I was so in the...
No, no, that's the fingerprint.
And then here you did the...
Yeah.
So that's fine.
Yeah, this is only the fingerprint.
No, no, no, no.
That's not the private key.
The private key looks way different.
Okay, okay.
No, you're good, you're good.
All right.
Yeah, I'm going to delete it.
This was temporary.
No, that's fine.
That's okay to include that,
because those are the instructions on how you generate the key.
With the laptop I was doing the temporary thing, I'm going to do the SSI to move to the server.
Oh yes.
Because I have very less space on my laptop.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, no go ahead and use your server.
We will keep on increasing the storage in the future assignments?
No, no.
So if you can feed dataset 1, 2, and 3, and you can run the stuff, that's enough.
For 50GB?
Yeah, 50GB is enough, yeah.
I felt like we will increase the ability to everything.
No, no, no, no, no.
50 gigabytes is to accommodate if you duplicate your data as well.
You'll see, because you'll have to answer in programming assignment, too, right?
How big is data set one, two and three?
You'll see they're not really that large.
For the hardware storage, I use the QCOW.
Yeah, so there are different formats.
Yeah, and it's still 50 gigs, but it doesn't take up 50 gigs immediately on my system.
Yeah, so right, they allow nowadays the virtual machines when they create a virtual hard drive to just increase the size as it's needed until it reaches a capacity.
Yeah.
Right, this allows you to actually run multiple VMs, right, and as long as they don't reach the capacity, it's fine.
Yeah, so.
Yeah, but for this assignment, it doesn't really matter what you use, you know, it's fine.
And those details would matter once you start running services in the cloud
and whatever, you know, or for other people or other businesses, you know,
that's when it matters because they have ability to do snapshots and, you know,
backups and incremental backups.
And, you know, that's where it becomes more useful.
Yeah, it was giving them up in the snapshot.
Yeah, yeah, no need to do backups for this.
It's fine.
The code is in GitLab, so as long as you do Git push very regularly,
should be fine now I don't have backup no I do have backup oh yeah I need to
modify that no no it used to be it used to be github but github discontinued
github classroom which I used to use in the past so they don't have that service
anymore yeah so you cannot create new classrooms and stuff and then they said
you know go use a third party the cost money I'm not gonna pay
I'm gonna host self hosted.
That's what happens with Microsoft on GitHub?
Of course, yeah.
I just read so many documentation yesterday where I was stuck.
Alright good!
I'm glad they're having fun.
I mean it's important for a class I think to be challenging but not too challenging
where you get discouraged but not too easy when you don't learn.
Anyways, I've been trying to balance this class for a long time, but we'll see.
There's always room if you want to do more.
There's so many things you can do with this assignment.
I do want to ask, like, I've studied the programming languages before,
but you were talking about a resource website, if you want to just...
Yeah, if you...
Should I email about that?
Yeah, email me and I can send you some resources.
The most resources that I have is for C++ and Java.
I feel like for Rust and Go, you have very good documentation now.
I just found for C++ and Java.
yeah just send me an email and i'll send you some links you know that is for c plus plus
there's a c programming.com it's a website designed by again another engineer who wrote
very cool i think i think i yeah that's very good it has very good instructions on how to you know
that's the resource that i usually give so very good intros and how to use the basics of the c and
in C++ language with explanations, exercises you can do.
Very nice.
And then for Java, trying to remember,
I think it's a webpage from Oracle
where it's kind of structured similarly,
where you have details about all of the data structures
that you can store data in,
or the collections data structures,
or all of the hashback data structures,
or all of the algorithms.
You can take a look and they have explanations
about how to use all of them.
It's very nice and structured.
So they can send me an email,
and I'll share with you those links.
They're not like a mystery or anything, but it's just something that I found very useful over the years.
Yeah.
I just have a screenshot of one of the, what you said, like the C programming and LensC.org too.
And I think there's also LensCPP, C++, C++.com.
There's like a lot of material.
Yeah.
And then, you know, lastly, what you want to do is after you learn the basics of the C++ language in Java,
you then want to learn how to use the API manual.
So for C++, it is cppreference.com, which shows, actually, it's a website that shows
you all of the functions and algorithms and data structures that you can use from the
standard library.
And there's a lot of them.
So you don't have to reinvent the wheel, actually, when you do programming.
Anyway, send me a link.
If you want, schedule an appointment for office hours and then I'll be able to explain more.
Okay.
I would probably ask for an extension on this assignment.
Yeah, I want to redo it.
If you can convince your other colleagues to ask, and when I get 30%, I'll give an extension for everyone.
Ok.
Thank you.
Quick question.
These do you want your mind?
Yeah.
.
We also talked about virtualization between the difference between virtual machines and containers.
Ok.
Yes. Yes.
But there's a few differences there.
Yeah. Like I heard about Docker and Docker uses containers and virtual machines.
That sounds like a lot of fun.
All the best, good luck.
Thank you.
okay
oh
Thank you.
um
you
Thank you.
.
You
Thank you.
.